<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The gale of opportunity. Or, A sermon preached (at Lidbury-North) at the funerall of the worshipfull Humphrey Walcot, of Walcot, Esq. June 8, 1650 and now published, by Thomas Froysell, Minister of the Gospell at Clunne in Shropshire.</title>
            <author>Froysell, Thomas, d. ca. 1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84939</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2249A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R177209</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45789324</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45789324</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172634</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84939)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172634)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2641:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The gale of opportunity. Or, A sermon preached (at Lidbury-North) at the funerall of the worshipfull Humphrey Walcot, of Walcot, Esq. June 8, 1650 and now published, by Thomas Froysell, Minister of the Gospell at Clunne in Shropshire.</title>
                  <author>Froysell, Thomas, d. ca. 1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.S. and are to be sold by H.B. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Item at 2264:19 is incorrectly identified as Wing F2249A in reel guide.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Dr. Williams's Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Walcot, Humphrey, 1586-1650.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John XII, 8 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172634:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>GALE</hi> OF OPPORTUNITY.</p>
            <p>OR, A SERMON Preached (at <hi>Lidbury-North</hi>) at the Funerall of the Worſhipfull <hi>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MPHREY WALCOT,</hi> of Walcot, Eſq; JUNE 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1650.</p>
            <p>And now Publiſhed, by <hi>Thomas Froyſell,</hi> Miniſter of the GOSPEL at <hi>Clunne</hi> in <hi>Shrop-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>As we have therefore opportunity, let us doe good unto all men, eſpecially to them that are of the Houſhold of Faith,</hi> 
                  <bibl>Gal. 6. 10.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exhort one another daily, while it is called to day, leſt any of you bee hardned through the deceitfulneſſe of ſin,</hi> 
                  <bibl>Heb. 3. 13.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Filij hominum uſquequo gravi corde? ut quid diligitis vanitatem et quaeritis Mendacium? Tempus hocanimabus non corporibus enim aſſignatum, dies ſalutis utique non voluptatis. Omnia tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus habent: Animabus nunc operam dare neceſſe eſt; nam in carne qui ſeminat, ſolum exinde metet corruptionem. <bibl>
                     <hi>St. Bernard</hi> in declamat.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>H. B.</hi> at the Signe of the <hi>Caſtle</hi> in <hi>Corne-hill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:172634:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172634:2"/>
            <head>To the truly vertuous and his much Honored, Miſtris <hi>Anne Walcot</hi> of <hi>Walcot.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was your Husbands deſire (when alive) that I ſhould preach His Funerall, and 'tis yours, that I ſhould Print it; Elſe (for ought I know) it had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeen the light: For I count not any of my Grapes worth the Preſſe: Therefore ſince it is your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſee this Sermon in a Printed dreſſe, I pray accept of it.</p>
            <p>When your deare Husband was alive, Yee were Two pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Diamonds ſet in the Ring of Marriage; God hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken him away to ſhine in another World, and hath left you to ſhine a while in this world; <hi>It is but a while,</hi> and therefore ſpread forth all your beams, before you ſet in the Weſt of Death, and be ſeen here no more.</p>
            <p>If we would ſhine with God in Heaven, we muſt ſhine for God on Earth: Let this Sermon of opportunities make you improve your opportunities: Shall the men of this world hugg their opportunities for the world, and ſhall not we Husband our opportunities for Heaven?</p>
            <p>Society with <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> even on this ſide Heaven, is a kinde of Heaven; and thoſe Chriſtall ſtreams of Joys which we might ſuck from God here, outid all the pleaſures and braveries of this world; which made <hi>Bonaventure</hi> (when the Devil tempting him, told him, he was a Reprobate, and<note place="margin">Si Non datur frui Deo et virtute poſt hanc vitam, fruamur eo in praeſenti.</note> therefore perſwaded him to drinke in the preſent pleaſures of this life, for (ſaith he) Thou art excluded from the future joyes with God in Heaven) Anſwer, No, not ſo, Satan, If I muſt not injoy God after this life, yet let me injoy him as much as I can in this life: Oh that drooping Soules would thus quench Satans ſuggeſtions! This were enough to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound all his temptations back againe upon him. <hi>Fruition of God a far off in this life (though we ſhould never injoy him in the next) is much better, then all the pleaſures of the world below him:</hi> Ah! What then will our fruition of him in Heaven be? Joy in him here, and you ſhall enjoy him hereafter: Live to him here, and you ſhall live with him hereafter: And to this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd God gives you all your opportunities, to this high and happy end, that you may attaine him. That himſelfe, and all that he
<pb facs="tcp:172634:3"/> is worth may be yours: And let me tel you, 1 That a Sermon of opportunities is almoſt as neceſſary to be preached, as to preach Chriſt himſelfe: becauſe the opportunity to receive Chriſt is (in its kinde) as neceſſary as Chriſt to be received: as Chriſt is called <hi>Salvation;</hi> ſo our opportunity is called the <hi>Day of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: Behold now is the accepted time, behold now is the day of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> We looſe Salvation it ſelfe, if we looſe the day of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; we looſe Chriſt himſelfe, if we let paſſe the day of Chriſt, <hi>If thou hadſt knowne, in this thy day, the things which belong unto</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 6. Luke 19. 42.</note> 
               <hi>thy peace, but now they are hid from thine eyes.</hi> A man that is to have a ſumme of money tendred him upon ſuch a day, muſt be ſure to watch and wait the day, if he would receive the money: He that hath a ſuite at Law, muſt obſerve the Terme-time; if he looſe the Terme he will looſe his ſuite: as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid, that <hi>Much of Religion conſiſts in Adverbs:</hi> ſo ſay I, That much weight of our Salvation lyeth in circumſtances, in the circumſtance of time and opportunity: As the whole weight of our Salvation is laid upon Chriſt, ſo the whole weight of our getting Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is layd upon our time, our opportunity: 2 Let Faith give you a preſentiality of things to come, of Death to come, of your Account to come: Faith gives them a preſent Exiſtence: ſet the Period of your Time neer unto you, behold it is at hand, when you ſhall live no longer, pray no longer, have the helpe of Ordinances no longer; We know not how few ſands are left in our Glaſſe of opportunity, and when they are once ſpent, God will not turne the Glaſſe againe for us: 'Tis this that affects the heart: 'Twas this that awaked <hi>Niniveh</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: <hi>Yet forty dayes, and Niniveh ſhall be deſtroyed:</hi> How did this Alarum ſtirre their Hearts! what (ſay they) but forty dayes? Are our dayes ſhut up into ſo narrow a roome? What are Forty dayes? How ſoon will they ſee an end? This fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them into a fit of Repentance: It is time for us (ſay they) to faſt and pray, and riſe out of ſin, if our Sun be ſo neer ſetting: I am perſwaded if God had ſent <hi>Jonah</hi> with this meſſage, <hi>Yet forty years and Niniveh ſhall be deſtroyed,</hi> it had made no worke at all upon them: it might have amazed them, but not ſtarted them up to ſuch a preſent repentance: It is the neer approach of our end that drives the worke home in us: Tell a Scorner in his ruffe and jollity, that he muſt dye one day; He receives it careleſly, and makes nothing of it: but tell him, yet forty
<pb facs="tcp:172634:3"/> dayes, and you muſt be called to judgement, Nay Sir, but two or three dayes hence, and dye you muſt; This goes to the quick, at this news the proud Ruffler is ſodainiy diſmounted, and his courage degraded, he looſes his blood in his cheeks, and ſhivers at the heart, like the leaves of the forreſt that are ſhaken with the winde: Ah then, ſee death upon us: Look upon our end as ſtanding by us; as neer as are the ſhadow and the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſo neer are Life and Death; our life is but the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, death brings ſubſtance with it, ſubſtantiall woes, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall joyes in the boſome of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cato</hi> Had oftentimes ſpoken in the Senate, that the City <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage</hi> muſt be deſtroyed, being too neer a neighbour to the City of <hi>Rome:</hi> For a long time together he formed no <hi>Oration</hi> in the Senate, but he uſherd in that ſtill as the concluſion: yet he could not carry it, becauſe <hi>Scipio Naſica</hi> being made up of a contrary opinion, alwayes pleaded on the other ſide, that it was for the good of the <hi>Romane Common-wealth</hi> that <hi>Carthage</hi> ſhould ſtand: At laſt, <hi>Cato</hi> on a day brought a green Fig into the Senate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and told them, that this Fig was growing in <hi>Carthage</hi> but three dayes agoe: and thereby warned them that a Navy might within three dayes arrive from <hi>Carthage,</hi> and lay fiege to their City: When they heard this, The neerneſſe of the danger, made ſuch impreſſion on their thoughts, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as before they could never be won upon to aſſent, now they voted not to give over till they leveld <hi>Carthage</hi> to the ground: And ſhall not eternity affect us? the neerneſſe of it write deep Characters of feare and care upon our hearts? Within three dayes, and death may lay ſiege to our City, to our Soul: beware of evill at hand, of death at hand, of Judgement at hand. Thou Fool (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>This night thy Soule ſhall be required of thee:</hi> ah then let us Act betimes, let not the night take us in a night, let not the night of Death take us in a night of ſin and ſecurity, then we ſhall have a double night at once upon us.</p>
            <p>3 Opportunities are very precious: Every one according to the objects they lay out for, value their opportunities: ther's no Prince or great perſon in the world, hath more Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents and attendants, then opportunity hath: All ſorts Court her, and wait with humbleſt ſervice on her: The Husbandman waits opportunity to plow, and ſow, and reap: The Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb facs="tcp:172634:4"/> attends opportunity to make his bargains at loweſt rate, and ſell off his wares at higheſt price: The Ambitious man ſtands at the door of opportunity to raiſe himſelfe: All (but fools) according to their occaſions runne out to meet, and bow the knee to opportunity, and ſhall not the <hi>deareſt</hi> opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties be precious to us? ſhall we not take the <hi>beſt</hi> opportunity by the hand? Opportunity to gaine the moſt precious things is the moſt precious opportunity; opportunity to get the beſt treaſures is the beſt opportunity: <hi>Godlineſſe is great gaine.</hi> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is the higheſt advancement, The Soule is the Crowne and Maſter-piece of man, ſurely then the opportunity to get and ſave theſe ſhould be counted precious opportunity: All things here (that are of the world) are but nothings, but Idols and ſhadows of the beſt things (<hi>and an Idol is nothing.</hi>) Time is<note place="margin">1 Cor. 8. 4. <hi>Tempus <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> but the Idol of Eternity, and things Temporall, but the Idol of things Eternall: Our eſtate and our dayes here are but an Idol: Ther's no divinity nor immortality in them: but God is an abſolute and eternall Being, the ſpring of all Divine ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions, They that live in him, live at an high rate, and live for ever: How can he complaine to want light, that lives in the midſt of the Sun? How can he complaine of Thirſt, out of <hi>whoſe belly flow rivers of living water?</hi> Surely then opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to injoy God, is the moſt precious opportunity.<note place="margin">John 7. 38.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Your Importunity hath ſetcht out this Sermon of Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity from me: and I have given you here more then I preach't, the time being too narrow to deliver all at once, and therefore I was faine to omit many things in the Pulpit, which I had in my papers: The Spirit of the Lord Preach it all over againe to our hearts: I commend you to the Lord,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Who am Yours moſt deeply obliged to Honour and Serve you, Tho. Froyſell.</signed>
               <dateline>Clunne <date>Octob. 8. 1651.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:172634:4"/>
            <head>To his highly HONORED, M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>John Walcott,</hi> of WALCOT. Eſquire.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, In publiſhing this Sermon (Preached at your Fathers Funerall) I could not but publiſh your Name to it, or it to your Name, you beeing ſo neer to him, for <hi>Every Child is the Father multiplied:</hi> He loved you dearly, for his (and your owne) ſake, I cannot but love and honour you highly.</p>
            <p>This Sermon was Preached for him, but it was Preached to you; and therefore God looks that it ſhould worke upon you: For at that time you had two Preachers at once Preaching to you, the Preacher in the Coffin, and the Preacher in the Pulpit: He preacht to you that you muſt dye, This Sermon preach't to you how you muſt live: His Death preach't to you, that time will be gone; This Sermon Preacheth to you, how you ſhould improve your time: <hi>As Death is the way to eternall life, ſo an holy life is the way to an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py death:</hi> Your Good Father dyed old, and you may dye young: as God writes ſome mens life in words at length, ſo ſometimes God is pleaſed to write in ſhort-hand, and cut a long life into a ſmall Monoſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable: and therefore turne and winde your preſent ſtock of time to the beſt, and grow rich in grace upon it. Remember</p>
            <p>1 You cannot begin too ſoon to ſerve Jeſus Chriſt: One may begin too late, but he can never begin too ſoon to ſerve Chriſt: Where ſhould the Flower of your Age grow but in the Garden of his ſervice?<note place="margin">Bp. Hall.</note> It is the Policy of the Devill to diſcourage Early holineſſe: He that goes out betimes in the morning, is more like to diſpatch his Journey, than he that lingers till the day be ſpent.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:172634:5"/>
            <p>2 You can never doe too much for Jeſus Chriſt: Religion know sno <note n="a" place="margin">Religio non poteſt habere exceſſum ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quantita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem abſolu. am, poteſt tamen ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere exceſſum ſecundum quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titatem propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis, prout ſcilicet in cultu divino fit ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid quod fieri non debet. Aqui. 22ae. q. 92. a 1. ad. 3.</note> exceſſe: you cannot ſavour too much of holineſſe: as there be ſome perſons that cannot beare the ſmell of Muske and ſweet perfumes, it fils their brains and makes them ſick, ſo Hypocrites, (and they are Hypocrites that) cannot abide the ſmell of holy preciſeneſſe, and the ſent of ſtrictneſſe: Paul bids us be ſervent in ſpirit [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, ſeething hot] ſerving the Lord: <hi>Quinon zelat, non amat,</hi> He that hath not zeale for Chriſt, hath not love to Chriſt: <hi>True zeale is a Seal of our Election:</hi> Strictneſſe and exactneſſe is the beauty and luſtre of Religion: I ſay, you cannot doe too much for Jeſus Chriſt, be hath done ſo much for us: And what doth Chriſt require of you, but he did the ſame for you? Is hee not upon equall termes with you? Nay before hand with you? If he cals you to bear the Croſſe for him, did he not bear a greater Croſſe for you? Grace puts no limits to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe:<note place="margin">Sus non poteſt ferre roſas &amp; amaracum. Franz. &amp; Plin. <hi>Rom. 12. 11.</hi> Iracundi ſunt qui amant. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian. in dial. Merc. &amp; Maij Finis appetitio non habet limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes defini. o;. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtot. Finis praeſcribit me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia, ſed ipſi fini non praeſcribi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Eccl. 7. 29. Gen. 1. 26.</hi>
               </note> He that makes God his End, thinks he can never have enough of God, or bee too holy for God: And though his actions of Holineſſe, and his forwardneſſe in them over-run his Credit, or over-throw his Eſtate, yet he cares not, repents not; for 'tis not his End to preſerve himſelfe, but to ſerve Jeſus Chriſt upon him ſelfe.</p>
            <p>3 Holineſſe is no upſtart: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>under which notion the world lookes upon it: as if preciſeneſſe in Religion were a new faſhion taken up, and put on by ſome but of late: No; Holineſſe was the firſt Suite that ever was put upon the back of mans nature: 'Tis elder then Sin: 'Tis the firſt borne: God made man Righteous: 'Tis more naturall to man to be righteous; Sin is againſt nature: Tis a defect of nature: It came (as I may ſay) of the wrong ſide of the Hedge, a meer Baſtard: God is not the Parent of it, it hath nothing of God in it, 'twas the Devil that begat it upon mans nature, and therefore 'tis of a later Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then grace, Grace was, when ſin was not: <hi>Let us make man</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>in our Image, after our likeneſſe:</hi> You ſee Grace is of a moſt ancient houſe, of the higheſt antiquity, and therfore if any thing will, it will ennoble you.</p>
            <p>4 And that you may be beated into zeale for Jeſus Chriſt, Live in the Scripture fire: as the Salamander (they ſay) lives in the fire, ſo doo you live in the Scripture, as your Element: It will ſcorch you into en holy love to Jeſus Chriſt: No book becomes your hand like the Bible: It made <hi>David</hi> wiſer then his Teachers: 'Tis this Book that makes Preachers, and this Booke is the beſt Preacher: This Booke will preach to you in your Chamber: By this Booke all Preachers and Hearers muſt be judged at the laſt day: This Booke will expound
<pb facs="tcp:172634:5"/> to you that hidden Booke that is within you, your Conſcience-: The Booke of Conſcience is a ſecret and intricate piece, very few are well read in it, moſt deceived by it; but this Booke of Scripture I ſay, this Booke will diſcover it, and ſhew you all the Errata in it; it will ſearch your very heart, and tell all its ſecrets to you, nay this Book will tell out Gods heart to you, and his minde concerning you,<note n="cc" place="margin">Ego odi li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bros meos, &amp; ſaepe opto eos in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terire, quod metuo ne moren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur lectores, &amp; abducant a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione ipſius Scripturae, quae ſola omnis ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae fons eſt, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Luther</hi> hated his owne Bookes, and (ſaith hee) <hi>I often wiſh they were all loſt, fearing leaſt they ſhould hold Readers in delay, and take them off from reading Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ierome</hi> gives a ſtrange narrative of himſelfe, how he was dragged to the Tribunall, becauſe he had read <hi>Cicero</hi> more greedily then he did the Scripture; Being asked of my condition, (ſaith he) I anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I was a Chriſtian: Thou lyeſt (ſaith the Judge) <hi>Ciceronianus es, non Chriſtianus:</hi> Thou art a Ciceronian, not a Chriſtian; for <hi>where thy Treaſure is, ther's thy heart alſo.</hi> Preſently (ſaith he) <hi>I was put to ſilence, and had not a word to ſay:</hi> and among the ſtripes (for he had commanded me to be beaten) I was ſcorched more with the fire of Conſcience conſidering with my ſelf that Verſe, <hi>In the Grave who will give thee thanks?</hi> Then I began to cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Have</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 6.</note> 
               <hi>mercy upon me, O Lord, have mercy upon me:</hi> This voice ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed loud amidſt the ſcourgings: At laſt, they that ſtood by, caſting themſelves downe at the Preſidents knees, prayed him, that he would pardon my youth, and give place of Repentance to my Errour: Then he requiring puniſhment, if at any time I read heathen Books, I, who in ſuch a caſe would have promiſed greater matters, began to ſweare deeply, ſaying, Lord, If at any time I ſhould read thoſe ſecular Books I have denyed thee: And ſo upon this Oath he was diſmiſſed: And he addes moreover, Neither was this a ſleep or a vaine dreame, with which we are often deluded, Witneſſe that Tribunall before which I lay; witneſſe that ſevere judgement which I trembled at, that I pray God I never fall again into ſuch examination by torment: I confeſſe I had my ſhoulders black and blew, and felt the blowes after my ſleep, and have ſince read Gods word with ſuch endeavour, as I never read before any humane writings: Thus far Saint <hi>Jerome:</hi> Now let this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage awake you, and all of us: Let us lay aſide the ſublimeſt curioſities of mans witt, all Volumnes for Scripture, And all imployment for Heaven.</p>
            <p>Wing your haſte, you have the flouriſhing plumes of Age upon you, How farre might you fly and ſoar up quite to an heaven of experience, and communion with Jeſus Chriſt, if you would looſe no time: I ſay,
<pb facs="tcp:172634:6"/> if you would looſe no time: I hope you will not, I pray you may not: For you may ſee in this Sermon, That opportunity is an unvaluable Treaſure, and yet a tranſient Treaſure; it carrieth laſting things along with it, and yet it ſelfe laſts not, ſtayes not with us: You may ſee in this Sermon, what great things you may looſe, if you looſe your op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>protunity; you may looſe your ſelfe if you looſe your opportunitie.</p>
            <p>God hath ſet you upon the higher ground, above many in the world, Act highly for him: Lay up a Rich ſtock of Grace within you, that you may have an heart to act for him in publick: I wiſh you proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity here, felicity hereafter: Accept t his Dedication from him, who doth, and ſhall ever reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your real Servant in <hi>CHRIST JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi> THO. FROYSEL.</signed>
               <dateline>CLUN. <date>
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 8. 1651.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:172634:6"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>JOHN XII. VIII.</bibl>
               <q>For the Poore alwayes yee have with you, but me yee have not alwayes.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ee-thinks I ſee a ſad concourſe of people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me this day; and truly who can be here and not bee ſad? A great man and a good man is fallen this day: He lived amiable, and dyed deſirable; I am perſwaded, you could all finde in your hearts to wiſh him into life againe, but that you are loath to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe God; Wee muſt ſubmit and kiſſe the hand of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the death of our deareſt Friends and Saints: We are now to performe our laſt office to him, wee have brought him from his houſe to his houſe, I meane his grave, which muſt houſe him up till the great day of the Reſurrection.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12. 5</note>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee what Death doth, it plucks up the tree by the roots. the <hi>Cedar</hi> as well as the <hi>Shrub:</hi> To day we are green, within a little while we are not ſeen: Stay but a few dayes, and ſuch a day as this will be thy day: And therefore that we may make a ſerious and ſpirituall uſe of this occaſion, turne your eye and caſt your thoughts upon the words of my Text.</p>
            <q>For the poore ye have alwayes with you, but me yee have not alwayes.</q>
            <p>Theſe words are the words of our Lord and Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and they are an Apology or Defence which he makes for a poor Saint, who having done a good worke (an act of love to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi>) was cenſured for it.</p>
            <p>1 The worke which was done, you ſhall ſee in the third <hi>ver. Then tooke Mary a pound of ointment, of Spikenard, very coſtly, and annointed the feet of Jeſus, And wiped his feet with her hair, and the Houſe was filled with the odour of the ointment:</hi> Obſerve,</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:172634:7"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſervation. </seg>
               </label> 1 The dear Saints are full of love to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 Love will ſpare no coſt: the Saints will ſpend the Spike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard of their credit, and the oyle of their life upon <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> where we dearly love Chriſt, nothing is too dear for him.</p>
            <p>2 You ſhall finde this worke of love ecclipſed, and cenſured in th 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>ver. Then ſaith one of his Diſciples, Judas Iſcariot, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Son which ſhould betray him, Why was not this ſold for three hundred pence, and given to the poore?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſervation. </seg>
               </label> There is no action ſo good, but ſome or other will be quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling with it, and finde ſome fault in it: The beſt actions are capable of cenſure and diſallowance: The nobleſt actions may have a ſcarre of reproach and cenſure put upon them:</p>
            <p>And this he ſaid (ſaith the 6. <hi>verſe) not that he cared for the poor, but becauſe he was a Thiefe, and had the bag, and bare what was put therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſervation. </seg>
               </label> Avarice wants not beautifull pretences: Hypocrites carry foul ſins under a fair vail.</p>
            <p>3 Now follows Chriſts Apology and Defence of her, <hi>v. 7. Then ſaid Jeſus, Let her alo ne</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſervation. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> will take his Saints part and plead their cauſe<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hil nocet ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uniator, ſi te <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> tua opera pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t Deus.</hi> Ferus.</note> againſt the wicked.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> pleads and juſtifies her action by two arguments.</p>
            <p>1 The one Argument, from the end of the action, <hi>The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ver. 7. [<hi>Againſt the day of my burying hath ſhe kept this</hi>] That is, yee doe willingly allow ſweet balmes and rich perfumes for the dead: Now I am within a little of death; Behold this woman hath herein reached beyond your conceit, ſhe hath done this (as her laſt office) toward my buriall: I hope you will affoord me thoſe ſolemnities of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which are given to others at their buriall; now, againſt the day of my Buriall hath ſhe kept this.</p>
            <p>2 The other Argument of defence he takes from the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of it; ſhe hath now an opportunity to ſhew me kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aeſens pro fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o, ut infra.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. 16. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. 28. 20.</note> which within a little while will be taken from her [<hi>For the poor alwayes you have with you, but me yee have not alwayes</hi>] and therefore let her ſhew me kindneſſe while ſhe may: <hi>Yee have not me alwayes with you:</hi> that is, yee ſhall not have me alwayes with you: Indeed, <hi>I am with you alway, even unto the end of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:172634:7"/> world,</hi> in reſpect of my divine preſence, <hi>but me yee have not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes with you,</hi> in reſpect of my humane preſence. Six dayes hence I dye, and goe to Heaven, I goe quite away from you, and you ſhall neither ſeeme, nor have me againe among you to performe any ſuch offices of reſpect to me, and therefore as for this action, ſhe doth well to take the opportunity, which will be taken from her. Obſerve, and 'tis the point I ſhall diſcourſe of at this time;</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">The Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>There is an opportunity for good, which if we neglect, we may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have the like againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore <hi>Marke</hi> rendreth it thus, <hi>for you have the poore</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 14. 7.</note> 
               <hi>with you alwayes, and whenſoever you will you may doe them good, [i. e.</hi> at any time] <hi>but me</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>yee have not alwayes.</hi> That is, you ſhall never want the opportunity of ſhewing kindneſſe to the poor, for yee ſhall never want poor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you; the poor that want, you ſhall not want among you, they ſhall always dwell among you, ſome poor or other as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of your Charity: but you cannot always performe ſervice to me in my body, for you ſhall not have mee always in this viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble forme and preſence with you. And therefore be not angry with this woman, in that whilſt I am preſent in body, ſhee hath done this ſervice to my body; The houre is comming you ſhall wiſh to doe the like, but cannot; The opportunity will be<note place="margin">Luke 17. 22.</note> gone, when I am gone, ye ſhall deſire to ſee one of the dayes of the Son of man, and ye ſhall not ſee it: And therefore I ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Docemur hoc verbo, ut non ceſſemus bene o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perari, quando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> et quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diu occaſionem habemus, non e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim ſemper id poterimus.</hi> Ferus <hi>in Loc.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is an opportunity of good, which if we neglect we may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have the like againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Time and opportunity differ: Time is the duration or ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of hours; days, or years, opportunity is a concurrence of all other helps with time to crowne your deſires, and give birth to your deſignes: opportunity is a meeting of time and means together to effect the end, when time and the means are married and lodged together they beget opportunity.<note place="margin">What opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is, <hi>Occaſionem pars Temporis, habens in ſed alicuius rei idoneam fuciendi aut non faciendi opportunit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tem.</hi> Cicero <hi>lib. 1. de invent.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>As the Marriner that intends a voyage, Riggs his Ship, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ready in the Haven, and waits the winde, his time is all the time he ſtayes there: His opportunity is when time, and tide, and winde, and all other accommodations meet together to ſend him away.</p>
            <p>If you would ſpeak with a man upon ſuch a day, your time is any hour in the day, but your opportunity to ſpeak with
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172634:8"/> him is, when he is at home, and can be at leiſure, and will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, ſpatium temporis in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> vero opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas Rei geren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dae, quam</hi> Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentius <hi>articu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum vocat</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor. <hi>in</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Iſai. 55. 6.</note> you his company: When all theſe claſpe together, that's your opportunity: So ſuppoſe thy buſineſſe be-to ſpeake with God, and ſeek him for grace or comfort, thy time to ſpeake with God is all thy life time, but thy opportunity to ſpeak with God is, when he is at home, and can be found; when he gives thee a heart to ſpeak to him, and hath a heart to ſpeak with thee, and therefore ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Seek yee the Lord while he may be found, call yee upon him while he is neer:</hi> when all theſe are twiſted together, that's the thread of thine opportunity.</p>
            <p>Time without opportunity is like a body without the Soule, a dead thing and meer inanimate carcaſſe, and as the body is left without the Soul, ſo is time many times left without her opportunity.</p>
            <p>So that time may ſtay, when opportunity is loſt: time may be preſent when opportunity Is paſt: the tree of time may<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſtand when the leaves of opportunity are dropt of: The ſtump of time may ſtick faſt in the root, when the branches of oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity are cut down: the head of time may ſtand, when the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den haires of opportunity are fallen off: when opportunitie is gone, the head of time is bald.</p>
            <p>And therefore I ſay, that there is an opportunity for good, which if we neglect, we may never have the like againe.</p>
            <p>And this I will ſhew you in two things.</p>
            <p>1 There is an opportunity of receiving good, which if we neglect, we may never have the like againe.</p>
            <p>2 There is an opportunity of doing good, which if we neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, we may never have the like againe;</p>
            <p>There is an opportunity to get, and an opportunity to act; an opportunity to lay up, and an opportunity to lay out ſpiritual treaſures, which if we neglect we may never have the like again.</p>
            <p>1 I ſay there is an opportunity of receiving good, which if we neglect, may be we ſhall never have the like againe.</p>
            <p>1. Sometimes there is an opportunity to beget faith in us, which if we neglect we may never have the like againe; as you<note place="margin">Eſai. 7. 10, 11, 12.</note> may ſee in <hi>Eſai. And the Lord ſpake againe unto Ahaz, ſaying, Ask thee a ſigne of the Lord thy God, aske it either in the depth beneath, or in the height above: But Ahaz ſaid, I will not aske, neither will I tempt the Lord.</hi> Ask a Signe, where thou wilt, where thou thinkeſt it may be the greateſt miracle, and give thee the greateſt ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172634:8"/> either in the depth, or in the height, on earth, or in heaven.</p>
            <p>Ah what an opportunity had <hi>Ahaz</hi> here offered to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire him with faith! A miracle where he would, and what he would; for the Prophet <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ratio ſigni autem (quod certe magnum enim) Regi A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas relinqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur libera, quan velit eſſe &amp; habere, ſive in ſupremis, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve in infernis.</hi> Sam. Bohl. in Iſai.</note> preſcribes not what ſigne <hi>Ahaz</hi> ſhould ask, leſt haply the truth of the miracle might be ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but leaves it to the Kings owne option and free choice, whether he will have it towards the depth or height, in earth or heaven, if earth were too low for a miracle, to heigh then his faith, he ſhould have one as high as heaven.</p>
            <p>Ah ſweet opportunity! ah ſtrong opportunity to worke ſuch a faith in <hi>Ahaz,</hi> as to truſt God for ever! here was an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity for him to try God, to put the word of God to an experience; and ah! what ſcope had he? Aske <hi>a Signe in earth or Heaven,</hi> where thou wilt, and what thou wilt, I will not grudge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, any thing to mount thy faith beyond the Region of feare and doubting; to make thee and my people <hi>Iſrael</hi> beleeve in me, thy faith ſhall want for nothing to ſupport it; God gave him leave to be his owne Carver.</p>
            <p>As when a great friend comes to your houſe, you enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him in this Language, Sir, command all thats here, aske what you'l have, 'tis yours: So did God be ſpeak <hi>Ahaz,</hi> all that's in heaven or earth is, for this minute, at thy ſervice, the choiceſt miracle that heaven or earth can yeeld to banquet thy faith, command it, 'tis thine: what a rich table of opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty did God ſpread for him? What variety of diſhes [a ſign from Heaven or earth] did the Lord ſet before him, to entertaine and feaſt his faith? Thus doth God condeſcend to ſinners; when they will not come up to him, he comes downe to them: This was kindnes enough to ſtrike the fire of Faith out of the hardeſt flint: Ah what an opportunity was here loſt! and once loſt, 'twas loſt for ever: we read not that the like was ever offered <hi>Ahaz</hi> any more, but he grew worſe: when men deſpiſe Gods opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, they grow worſe and worſe.</p>
            <p>So againe, you have another ſad inſtance in the ſecond of <hi>Kings;</hi> where <hi>Eliſha</hi> prophecied in a time of ſcarcity, <hi>Thus ſaith</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kin. 7. 1. 2.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord, tomorrow about this time ſhall a meaſure of fine flowre be ſold for a Shekel, and two meaſures of barley for a ſhekel in the gate of Samaria; then a Lord on whoſe hand the King leaned, anſwered the man of God, and ſaid, Behold, If the Lord would make windows in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172634:9"/> heaven, might this thing be? and he ſaid, Behold Thou ſhalt ſee it with thine eyes, but ſhalt not eat thereof:</hi> And ſee this verified. <hi>And the King gave the Lord, on whoſe hand he leaned, the charge of the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 17.</note> 
               <hi>gate, and the people trod upon him in the gate, and he dyed as the man of God had ſayd.</hi> He ſeeth the plenty for conviction of his unbelief, but he dyeth and taſtes it not, as a puniſhment of his unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe.</p>
            <p>2. Sometimes an opportunity of repentance, and ſo of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving pardon, is given to a man, which if he neglect, he may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have the like againe: Such an opportunity <hi>Judas</hi> had: <hi>Judas</hi> had conceived a plot in the wombe of his intention to betray <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and form'd it up into a conſpiracy with the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees</hi> to deliver him to them, yet <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> gives him an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity once more to repent and recall himſelfe before it be too late; <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, one of you ſhall betray me, He that dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26. 21. 23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>his hand with me in the diſh, the ſame ſhall betray me. The Son of man goeth, as it is written, but woe unto that man by whom the Son of man is betrayed, it had been good for that man if he had not been borne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ah <hi>Judas!</hi> What a thunder-clap is here ſent from heaven to awake thee? what a warning-piece goeth off to ſcare thy ſoule out of ſin? 'Twas a providence thou ſhouldſt ſit at table once more with Chriſt, to heare ſomething fall from his lipps that might melt thy heart; Ah, what an opportunity hadſt thou now put into thine hand, to repent, and retract thy purpoſe? for the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> doth diſcover his ſin, and doth diſſwade him from his ſin.</p>
            <p>1 He doth diſcover the Sin,</p>
            <p>But not the perſon, yet.</p>
            <p>I ſay, He doth diſcover the ſin [<hi>one of you ſhall betray me</hi>] the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> diſcovers the ſin that he might recover the ſinner, He ſhewed him his ſin, that he might not ſin, he ſhewed him his ſin before hand, that he might not ſin underhand: he did ſtrike the ſin that he might open a veine of confeſſion in <hi>Judas,</hi> and make him bleed kindly: Ah what an opportunity was here for <hi>Judas</hi> to confeſſe and be forgiven?</p>
            <p>2 But he doth not diſcover the perſon yet: he doth not name him that he might not ſhame him: he opens the ſin but not the perſon, that he might thaw him and not harden him: that he might winne him, but not irritate and provoke him: <hi>Jeſus</hi> is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172634:9"/> yet tender of his credit, how much more of his Soul: what an heavenly dew of opportunity drops it ſelf upon <hi>Judas</hi> to moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten his heart?</p>
            <p>In like manner, what an opportunity haſt thou (O Sinner) to repent when God ſhall reprove thy ſecret Adulteries, and unjuſt dealings, and hypocriſie in a Sermon, and not diſcover yet?</p>
            <p>2 He doth diſſwade him from his ſin by two arguments.</p>
            <p>By Love, and Terrour;</p>
            <p>1 By Love, <hi>He that dippeth his hand with me in the diſh, the ſame ſhall betray me:</hi> which words were not ſpoken to diſcover <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> by this ſigne, but to aggravate his ſin; as if he ſhould ſay, my fellow-commoner, one of my familiar friends, that eats of the ſame diſh with me, ſhall betray me.</p>
            <p>And here Chriſt endeavours to melt the heart of <hi>Judas,</hi> and cauſe him to forbeare, by an argument fetcht from all the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and intimacy that had been ſo long between them: what, my friend? my familiar? who doth not onely ſit at the ſame Table with me, but eat of the ſame diſh with me, will he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray me? will that hand that hath been with me in the ſame diſh, dip and dye it ſelfe into a Crimſon colour in my blood? he diſſwades him by love, by the law of love and friendſhip.</p>
            <p>2 He diſſwades him by Terror: <hi>The Son of man goes as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26. 24.</note> 
               <hi>of him, but woe unto that man by whom the Son of man is betrayed, it had been good for that man if he had not been born:</hi> where obſerve,</p>
            <p>1 The Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> be wayles not himſelf, but <hi>Judas,</hi> even whilſt he threatens <hi>Judas,</hi> he pities <hi>Judas: woe unto that man by wom the Son of man is betrayed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 He doth not yet unmaske and diſcloſe <hi>Judas:</hi> he carries the perſon yet in the clouds, he doth not as yet ſay in <hi>indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duo,</hi> Woe to thee O <hi>Judas;</hi> but ſpeaks ſtill in the general, <hi>Woe to that man by whom the Son of man is betraied:</hi> the individual diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of <hi>Judas</hi> comes in afterwards, and here <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> does with this threatning way-lay <hi>Judas,</hi> to make him retreat,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Paena pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicitur, ut quem pudor non vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, corrigant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciata ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia.</hi> Hieronim <hi>in cap.</hi> 26. Mat.</note> ſeeking his ſalvation, <hi>It had been good for that man if he had not been borne:</hi> as if he had ſaid, if nothing elſe yet will, if nothing that hath been ſaid yet can recall the Traytor from his purpoſe of ſinning, yet let this one thing beſpeak him, and turne his heart quite about, his owne ſafety, his owne fearfull conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which will follow upon his ſin, let that put a ſtop to his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172634:10"/> progreſſe: <hi>Woe unto that man by whom the Son of man is betrayed, it had been good for that man if he had not been borne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the door of opportunity ſtood open to <hi>Judas,</hi> and <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſtood in the door to invite <hi>Judas,</hi> but he had not an heart to goe in, and the opportunity was preſently ſhut againſt him, and he never had the like againe: he goes away, and becomes his own Executioner; <hi>Judas</hi> betrayes Chriſt, and after be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayes himſelfe, when Chriſt called him, he would not repent kindly, and now he meets with an unkind repentance that Swallows him up in the gulph of deſpaire.</p>
            <p>3 A man may have an opportunity given him to ſave his life, and ſo by conſequent to ſave his ſoule, which if he neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects he may never have the like againe. I will give you two<note place="margin">Gen. 19. 12, 13, 14.</note> ſad inſtances, the one is <hi>Lots</hi> children in <hi>Sodome; Then the men ſaid unto Lot, whom haſt thou yet here, either Son in Law, or thy ſons or thy daughters, or what ſoever thou haſt in the City, bring it out of this place for we will deſtroy this place, becauſe the cry of them is great before the Lord, and the Lord hath ſent us to deſtroy it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note, </seg>
               </label> The Saints are ſo neer to God, that he will ſave thoſe that are neer to them, for their ſakes; God would be a friend to <hi>Lots</hi> friends, a father to his children. <hi>And Lot went out and ſpake unto his ſons in law which married his daughters, and ſaid, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p, get yee out of this place, for the Lord will deſtroy this City:</hi> Behold, here's their opportunity! an opportunity to ſave their lives from fire and brimſtone, and for ought I know, their ſoules from the fire of hell; O golden opportunity! for a mans life is his Treaſure, an opportunity to ſave ones life is the life of all opportunities, and therefore poore <hi>Lot</hi> goeth to them, <hi>Grace doth not extinguiſh nature:</hi> he flyeth upon wings of love to them, and tels them, he warnes them like a Prophet, and beſpeaks them like a Father: but what ſay they? <hi>he ſeemed as one that mocked to his ſons in Law;</hi> and ſo he leaves them, for his time was ſhort, and now their opportunity is gone, and they are gone too: Farewell now, you are all dead men and women: God firſt raines downe the golden drops of opportunity upon them to ſave their lives, which they neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and preſently he raines downe ſhowres of fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone on them, and takes away their lives.<note place="margin">1. Kings 22. 4, 5, 7, 8, 17. &amp; 28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Another inſtance is <hi>Ahab</hi> in the firſt of the <hi>Kings, Wilt thou goe with me to battel to Ramoth Gilead? and Jehoſhaphat ſaid to the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172634:10"/> King of I Iſrael, I am as thou art, my people as thy people, my horſes as thy horſes, and Jehoſhaphat ſaid unto the King of Iſrael, enquire I pray thee at the word of the Lord to day, And Jehoſhaphat ſaid, is there not here a Prophet of the Lord beſides, that we might enquire of him? And the King of Iſrael ſaid unto Jehoſhaphat, There is yet one man Michaiah the ſon of Imlah, by whom we may enquire of the Lord, but I hate him, for he doth not prophecie good concerning me, but evill: And Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſhaphat ſaid, Let not the King ſay ſo. And he ſaid, I ſaw all Iſrael ſcattered upon the hills as ſheep that have not a Sheapheard, and the Lord ſaid theſe have no Maſter, let them returne every to his houſe in peace: And Michaiah ſaid, if thou returne at all in peace, the Lord hath not ſpoken by me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here was his opportunity to ſave his life: but goe he will, his opportunity expires, and his life too, for he never returnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live againe, <hi>for a certaine man drew a Bow at a venture, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 34.</note> 
               <hi>ſmote the King of Iſrael between the joynts of the harneſſe, wherefore he ſaid unto the driver of his Chariot, Turne thine hand and carry me out of the Hoſt, for I am wounded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>[ certaine man drew a bow at a venture] the man ſhot the Arrow, but God aimed it: the man ſhot at a venture, but God leveld it at <hi>Ahab:</hi> the man ſhot at he knew not who, but <hi>Ahab</hi> in the whole Army was Gods marks-man; <hi>Carry me away ſaith</hi> Ahab <hi>out of the Hoſt for I am wounded:</hi> Oh <hi>Ahab;</hi> What thinkeſt thou now of Gods opportunities! What ſaiſt thou now of <hi>Micaihas</hi> words? <hi>I am wounded;</hi> ſaith <hi>Ahab,</hi> I beleeve thee, and the loſſe of thine opportunity wounds thee more; ther's death wounds in thy Soule, as well as in thy body.</p>
            <p>4 When an hypocrite will not obey Gods expreſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, he may loſe his heart, and his reſtraining grace for ever after; when a man loves a ſin better then Gods command, God leaves him to his ſin: When a man gives up himſelfe to a luſt, God finds a time to give him up alſo, and ſets him a go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faſter: he opens the ſluces, and puls downe the bankes, that the mans luſt may run in a full ſtream, and have nothing to check it.</p>
            <p>Sinner! God will one time or other try thee ſecretly, with a caſting command, a command that ſhall have the caſting voice, and ther's thine opportunity to make or marr thy ſelfe for ever.</p>
            <p>The Glaſſe of <hi>Balaams</hi> ſtory will ſhew you the face of this
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172634:11"/> truth in it, when King <hi>Balak</hi> ſent for <hi>Balaam</hi> to curſe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>Iſrael,</hi> God denyes him leave to goe, he ſets his command before<note place="margin">Num. 22. 12.</note> before him, <hi>Thou ſhalt not goe with them, thou ſhalt not curſe the people, for they are bleſſed:</hi> Here's <hi>Balaams</hi> opportunity: the command is ſet before him to try him to try him, and <hi>Balaam</hi> ſtands now upon the turning point, But what's the iſſue? When the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers came again, <hi>Balaam</hi> ſollicits God againe for leave to goe, <hi>Balack</hi> promiſes him tranſcendent and high rewards, and they ſeal a deep impreſſion upon the ſoft wax of his covetous heart, he is upon the wing to be gone, and what then? God<note place="margin">Verſ 20.</note> now in judgement gives him leave to goe; <hi>God came unto Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam at night, and ſaid unto him, It the men come to call thee, riſe up and goe with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how can theſe ſtand together? in the 12 verſe <hi>God ſaid unto Balaam, Thou ſhalt not goe with them;</hi> But in the 20. Verſe, <hi>If the men come to call thee, riſe up and goe with them;</hi> Why did God bid him what before he did forbid him? At the firſt time, when he told him, <hi>Thou ſhall not goe with them,</hi> God ſhewed him the will of his approbation, but when at the ſecond time God ſaid to him, <hi>Riſe up, and goe with them,</hi> 'twas a command with indignation.</p>
            <p>Some things God permits with indignation, not for that he gives leave to the act, but that he gives a man over to his fin in the act: This ſufferance implyes not favour, but judgement; God never liked <hi>Balaams</hi> Journey, he diſpleaſedly gives way to it.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>Balaam</hi> thine opportunity is loſt, and thou a loſt man: God will now give thee up to thine owne heart; <hi>Balaam</hi> after this grows worſe and worſe; his heart is given up and hardned, 'tis ſteept in ſottiſhneſſe, for an Angel ſtops him with a drawn ſword in the way, yet he hath a minde to goe, his Aſſe doth by miracle ſpeak, and yet he hath a minde to goe, ah <hi>Balaam!</hi> wher's thine underſtanding? I ſee now thou art a gone man, for thine Aſſe is wiſer then his Rider, the Aſſe becomes rationall, <hi>Balaam</hi> becomes brutiſh, when men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell Gods opportunities they become more brutiſh then the beaſts.</p>
            <p>5 A man may by one ſhort act of ſin bring a long curſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelfe and his poſterity: As <hi>Ham</hi> when he ſaw his Father <hi>Noah</hi> drunke, and uncovered in his Tent, Ah what an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172634:11"/> loſt he now? had he veiled his fathers nakedneſſe, and throwne a cloud over it, he had received a bleſſing: but he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and proclaimes it to his brethren, and they doe what he ſhould have done; they covered their Faterhs nakedneſſe, and would not turn their eys to ſee it. <hi>And Noah awoke from his wine, and knew what his younger ſon had done unto him, and he ſaid, Curſed is Canaan, a ſervant of ſervants ſhall he be unto his brethren. Canaan</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 9. 24, 25.</note> 
               <hi>was Hams</hi> ſon, <hi>Noah</hi> (<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nec enim tantum hominis verbum eſt, ſed Dei, imo plus &amp; polius eſt prophetia quam ultionis aviditas.</hi> Ferus in loc.</note> as Gods mouth) prophecieth a curſe upon the ſon, for the fathers ſin; although ſome thinke <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Non dubito filium ejuſdem cum patre inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nij fuiſſe, &amp; ipſum quoque, ut patrem ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſſe</hi> Noe, Mercer.</note> that <hi>Canaan</hi> firſt ſaw <hi>Noah</hi> naked, and deriding him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, called his father to bear him company in that contempt; Here <hi>Ham</hi> is curſed in his ſon <hi>Canaan,</hi> and a curſe entailed not onely to <hi>Canaan,</hi> but to his poſterity. <hi>Noah</hi> prophecies a long ſeries, and chaine of curſes upon <hi>Canaan</hi> and his children: he makes the curſe hereditary to the name and nation of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>A ſervant of ſervants ſhall he be unto his brethren;</hi> that is, the vileſt ſervant: for the <hi>Hebrews</hi> expreſſe the ſuperlative degree by ſuch a duplication, as [vanity of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities] that is, moſt vaine, a [ſong of ſongs] a moſt excellent ſong: So here, <hi>A ſervant of ſervants,</hi> that is, the vileſt ſervant: Ah heavy and prodigious curſe! for the Kernel and quinteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of this curſe was ſpirituall, whereby <hi>Canaan</hi> and his poſterity are ſealed up for ſlaves to ſin, and excommunicate from the Church of God: what a brave opportunity did <hi>Ham</hi> looſe here to get a large and long bleſſing on himſelfe and his poſterity? and this opportunity he loſt for ever: for the decree is gone forth, [a ſervants of ſervant ſhalt thou be.]</p>
            <p>Soul thy not obeying God in ſuch a nick of time may looſe thee, thou knoweſt not what: the doing or not doing of one<note place="margin">1 Sam. 10. 8.</note> act may undoe thee for ever: See another inſtance in <hi>Saul [And thou ſhalt goe downe before me to Gilgal, and behold I will come downe unto thee to offer burnt offerings, and to ſacrifice ſacrifi ces of peace-offerings, ſeaven dayes thou ſhalt tarry till I come to thee, and ſhew thee what thou ſhalt doe] And he tarried ſeaven dayes according to the ſet time that Samuel had appointed, but Samuel came not to Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, and the people were ſcattered from him, and Saul ſaid, bring hither a burnt offering to me, and peace-offerings, and he offered the burnt offering; and it came to paſſe that as ſoon as he had made an end of offering the burnt offering, behold Samuel came, and Saul went out
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172634:12"/> to meet him, that he might ſalute him: Samuel</hi> had bid <hi>Saul</hi> ſtay ſeven dayes in <hi>Gilgal</hi> till he came: ſix dayes he ſtayeth, and part of the ſeaventh, he had but a little part of a day to expect longer: his impatience will not give him leave, for he offereth Sacrifice before <hi>Samuel</hi> cames, and he had no ſooner offered ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice but <hi>Samuel</hi> come: <hi>As ſoon as he had made an end of offering</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 10.</note> 
               <hi>the burnt offering, behold</hi> Samuel <hi>came, and tels him, thou haſt done fooliſhly, for now,</hi> marke the word [now] <hi>now would the Lord</hi>
               <note place="margin">13.</note> 
               <hi>have eſtabliſhed thy Kingdome upon Iſrael for ever:</hi> This one op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity improved would have ſealed thee the Kingdome; one act of obedience now, would have given thee a laſting mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: this minute of time would have got thee a Crown: ſcarce is <hi>Saul</hi> warme in his Kingdome when he hath even loſt it: how neer may we be to a mercy and miſſe it? Couldſt thou not wait a little longer <hi>Saul?</hi> Thou waſt within an inch of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, within a haires breadth of an eſtabliſhed fruition: <hi>Saul</hi> waited till the ſeaſon, and then brake off: He got nothing by all his ſix days waiting, becauſe he watcht not this ſeaſon: and the reaſon is, becauſe though obedience at all times pleaſe God, yet there is a punctuall and peculiar ſeaſon of obedience, wherein he bleſſeth: all the other acts of obedience are but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratory, there is a ſpeciall nick and ſeaſon of obedience which crownes with bleſſing: perſeverance is the only grace that crownes a Chriſtian: <hi>Methuſelah</hi> lived nine hundred nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and nine years, if he had fallen away from grace at the nine hundred ninety and nine years end, all the good that he had done or got before had been quite forgotten: To obtaine a bleſſing, its not enough to obey God, but we muſt obey him in that point and nick of time wherein he will give the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; as to meet with a friend in a place; its not eneugh to walke there often, you may walke there a week together and not meet him, but you muſt walke there in that nick of time wherein he appoints you the meeting.</p>
            <p>6 There is ſometimes an opportunity given to receive ſome gift of the ſpirit, which if we neglect we ſhall never have the like againe: as you may ſee in <hi>Eliſha,</hi> when <hi>Eliſah</hi> was to leave the world, and to ride in ſtate to heaven in his Coach or bright Chariot, ſaith he to <hi>Eliſha, Ask what I ſhall doe for thee before I</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 2. 9, 10, 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>be taken away from thee, and Eliſha ſaid, I pray thee let a double portion of thy ſpirit be upon me, ſaith Elijah thou haſt asked an
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172634:12"/> bard thing; nevertheleſſe, if you ſee mee when I am taken from thee, it ſhall be ſo unto thee; but if not, it ſhall not be ſo: And it came to paſſe as they ſtill went on, and talked, that behold there appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a Chariot of fire, and horſes of fire, and parted them both a ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and</hi> Elijah <hi>went up by a whirlewinde into heaven, and</hi> Eliſha <hi>ſaw it, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here was a tickliſh opportunity, a ſlippery opportunity: had <hi>Eliſha</hi> miſſed it, he had never had the like againe: So mayſt thou have ſome gales and ruſhings in of the ſpirit, to put thee on to duty, ſome breathings of the ſpirit to blow up thy cold heart into holy heats and deſires; ſome coruſcations and beames of the ſpirit to enlighten thee, ſome joggings and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vokings to heavenly -mindedneſſe, ſome ſtrengthnings of the ſpirit againſt a luſt proffered thee, which if you put off it may be thou wilt never have the like againe.</p>
            <p>7 So when a man doth by providence injoy the ſociety and company of a godly man, that is, of a choice ſpirit; here he hath an opportunity to taſte fruit from him, which if he neglect, he may never have the like againe.</p>
            <p>A man may by providence be caſt upon the company and fruition of ſuch a precious and fruitfull Chriſtian, ſuch an experienced Chriſtian, that he ſhall hardly meet with ſuch a one againe in all his dayes: Ah! now how ſhouldſt thou im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove his graces whilſt thou haſt him? How ſhouldſt thou ſuck experiences from him? How ſoon he may be removed from thee, or thou from him, thou knoweſt not: providence that lends thee him and his graces for a while, may carry him from thee to another place; and then thou looſeſt thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not what: Ah! how will the loſſe of ſuch an opportunity afterward damp the ſpirit!</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Faelix,</hi> whilſt <hi>Paul</hi> was in priſon, enjoyed a rich op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity: he had a rich Jewel in the Casket of opportunity: Ah what an <hi>improvement</hi> might <hi>Faelix</hi> have made of <hi>Paul</hi> all that time? he had been happy <hi>Faelix</hi> then: Sometimes he ſent for<note place="margin">Act. 24. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> and heard him reaſon of righteouſneſſe, temperance and judgement to come; but he might have had more of <hi>Pauls</hi> company if he would: he knew not what a price he had in his hand whilſt he had <hi>Paul</hi> in his cuſtody: but he loſt his opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, for within two yeares he was removed, and never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed ſuch an opportunity againe: And thus I have done with. the firſt part.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:172634:13"/>
            <p>2 There are opportunities of doing good, which if we neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect me may never have the like again.</p>
            <p>1 When you are travelling, and fall in upon the way with a man you never ſaw before, and a thouſand to one never ſhall ſee againe; here's an opportunity for thee to doe his ſoul good, to drop heaven into his ſoul; which ſeaſon thou maiſt hever have againe to ſeaſon him with a word of grace: Thus <hi>Philip</hi> falling in with the <hi>Eunuch</hi> whilſt he was riding on his way homeward from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> cloſed with him and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<note place="margin">Act. 8. 35. 37.</note> Chriſt unto him, and was an inſtrument to ſave the ſoule of him whom he never ſaw before, nor ever after ſaw againe.</p>
            <p>2 When thou art in an office for a time, it may be but one yeare, thou art cloathed with authority and opportunity to doe good, which thou maiſt never have againe. Time will ſtrip thee of thy robes of Authority, thou mayſt lay down thy life before thou layſt downe thy office; if not, yet annuall offices expire, and fall off of themſelves, and when thine au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is gone, thy opportunity is gone: as a man that hath a ſword or a ſtaffe in his hand, if his ſtaffe be wrencht out of his hand, he hath loſt his opportunity to ſoile his enemy; ſo it is when the ſtaffe of authority is paſſed out of thy hand unto another, thy time is gone.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faelix</hi> whilſt he was in office, was married unto a gallant opportunity to releaſe <hi>Paul</hi> out of Priſon, but he did not hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band the opportunity, and he was divorced from it for ever,<note place="margin">Act. 24. 27.</note> for ſaith the Text, after two years <hi>Portius Feſtus</hi> came into <hi>Faelix</hi> room, and <hi>Faelix</hi> willing to ſhew the Jewes a pleaſure left <hi>Paul</hi> bound.</p>
            <p>3 So when a man is dying, upon his death-bed, there you have an opportunity to doe his ſoul good, which you ſhall never have againe: Thus Chriſt dropt in grace and good counſell into the thiefe upon Croſſe, the Croſſe, was his death-bead, which had it been omitted, the thiefs ſoul had been loſt within a few howres for ever, and the opportunity gone too.</p>
            <p>4 So when a friend is in affliction, then thou haſt an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to ſtrike whilſt the iron is hot, to humble him while he is humbled: to ſpeake a word in ſeaſon to him while his heart is ſeaſoning and melting: as the Jews and thoſe eaſterne people doe plough and ſow their ground when the former
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:172634:13"/> raine hath ſoftned it, Ah! Sow then (for now is the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity) I ſay, ſow the ſeed of inſtruction upon a ſinners heart, while the former or latter raine of affliction fals upon him, it is a ſoftning time, a melting time; while the raine drops, the earth is ſoft: He that made a ſcorne of godlineſſe before, will then be of another minde, and hear counſell then if ever he will hear it.</p>
            <p>5 So when a godly man is by providence caſt into a fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he hath an opportunity to diſtill ſhowres and drop divine influences, whilſt (like a ſtar) he is fixed there, which if he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, he may never have the like againe: thus <hi>Paul</hi> being in the Jaylors family preacht the Goſpell to him, and to his houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, and he beleived in God (ſaith the Text) with all his<note place="margin">Act. 16. 34.</note> houſhold.</p>
            <p>6 So when a Miniſter hath intereſts in the hearts of a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, let him improve it, and look to it, for he knows not how ſoon the tide may turne, and he never have the like oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 23.</note> againe.</p>
            <p>7 Rich men, You that are in proſperity and have your ſayles fil'd with gales of wealth, you have opportunities to honour God, which others have not, and which if you neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect you may ſuddenly never have the like againe.</p>
            <p>1 You have wherewith to maintaine and encourage the Goſpel, to give to the Saints; and truly it is the higheſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of riches, to make riches an inſtrument to advance reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: Oh then honour God with thy ſubſtance, lay out for God and his Goſpel, leaſt the Lord, thou knoweſt not how ſoon, ſend a North-wind to blow upon thee, and freez up thy wealth, and then thou mayeſt never have the like tide of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity againe.</p>
            <p>2 Beſides, you have greater opportunities for hearing the word, and praying in your ſecret cloſets, then poor men have, who live upon the ſweat of their brows: you may be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing when the poor muſt be labouring for their living, you may be meditating, whilſt, they muſt be getting their bread.</p>
            <p>If then you, rich ones, ſee poor men that are neceſſitated to work hard for a meane living, more lively, more frequent and abundant in duties then your ſelves are, know now you walke not by rule, where much is given, much is required; and to whom God hath given much, of them he asks the more;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:172634:14"/> who are happier, they that are in the Kitchin, or they that attend upon the Prince?</p>
            <p>Ah, you rich and great perſons! this is a high favour and tranſcendent honour, that God hath freed you from inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our drudgery, to imploy you in more noble ſervices in the Court, while others muſt ſerve their occaſions; you that have fulneſſe of the world, you have fulneſſe of time to injoy the Kings preſence, and wait upon Chriſts perſon in holy duties, and therefore know that you ſhould be more with God then others: Holineſſe is your trade, and your cloſets are your ſhops, and every day is a Sabbath day to you: Take your op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities; that may be enough for one which is too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle for another; where God gives much opportunities, they muſt doe much for God.</p>
            <p>8 A man may have an opportunity to ſuffer for Chriſt, which if he nglect he may never have the like againe: To ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for Chriſt is honorable, God will not put this honour up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every one, he puts this honour upon his veſſels of honour: he gives grace to a man, and caſts him into a veſſel of ſilver or gold, and then throws him into the fire to melt, and ſuffer for his name: The metal of that Chriſtian muſt be ſilver or gold that can ſuffer for Chriſt: a veſſel of wood, throw him into the fire, his hoops will fly off, hee'l breake aſunder, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hold out.</p>
            <p>The three children that were caſt into the fiery furnace, what glorious mould and metall were they made of? Had they not taken the opportunity to ſuffer for God, they might never have met with ſuch a one againe.</p>
            <p>1. For what a ſpreading ſame and glory of God did their ſufferings ſcatter over all the world? God is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and adored by <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> a Decree is made that every People, Nation, and Language which ſpeake amiſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the God of <hi>Shadrach, Meſback</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> ſhall be cut<note place="margin">Dan. 3. 28, 29.</note> in pieces: <hi>Then Nebuchadnezzar ſpake and ſaid, bleſſed be the God of</hi> Shadrack Meſhach <hi>and</hi> Abednego, <hi>who hath ſent his Angel, and delivered his ſervents that truſted in him, and have changed the Kings word, and yeelded their bodies, that they might not ſerve nor worſhip any God, except their own God. Therefore I make a Decree that every People, Nation or Language, which ſpeake any thing amiſſe againſt the God of</hi> Shadrach, Meſhach <hi>and</hi> Abed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nego,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:172634:14"/> 
               <hi>ſhall be cut in pieces, and their houſes ſhall be made a dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, becauſe there is no other God that can deliver after this ſort:</hi> Here Gods glory ſhines out of their ſufferings, even enemies acknowledge none like <hi>Iſraels</hi> God.</p>
            <p>Here they found a moſt glorious opportunity to honour God, which if they had loſt, they might never have had the like againe; had they loſt this opportunity God had loſt his glory.</p>
            <p>2 To honour themſelves: for</p>
            <p>1 They were no ſooner in the fire, but they met with <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 3. 24. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> there; <hi>Then Nebuchadnezzar the King was aſtonied, and roſe up in haſte, and ſpake and ſaid unto his Counſellors, Did not we caſt three men bound into the midſt of the fire? they anſwered and ſaid unto the King, True O King: He anſwered and ſaid, Lo, I ſee four men looſe walking in the midſt of the fire, and they have no hurt, and the forme of the fourth is like the Son of God:</hi> They were but three that were caſt into the fire, but <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> ſaw foure there: And the forme of the Fourth was like the Son of God: Whether it were <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the naturall Son of God, or an Angel, who are called the Sons of God, here was<note place="margin">Verſe 28. Job 1. 6.</note> a great honour; the Angels of the Lord are preſent with the Saints in their ſufferings, and <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is preſent with the Saints in their ſufferings: <hi>When thou paſſeſt through the waters I will be with thee, and through the Rivers they ſhall not overflow</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 43. 2.</note> 
               <hi>thee, when thou walkeſt through the fire thou ſhall not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle on thee:</hi> Angels company and Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany is a wondrous honour: We count it a great honour to have Princes to be our companions; the Saints in their ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings have Princes for their companions, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and his Angels: and thy ſuffering time is opportunity to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the company of theſe Princes and great ones.</p>
            <p>2 It was an honour to them, that God ſhould worke ſuch<note place="margin">Verſ 27.</note> a noble miracle for them, as to ſtop the mouth of the fire, that it could not burn them; <hi>And the Princes, Governours and Captains, and the Kings Counſellors being gathered together, ſaw theſe men upon whoſe bodies the fire had no power, nor was an haire of their heads ſinged, neither were their coats changed, nor the ſmell of fire had paſſed on them:</hi> Ah wonderfull! So did God honour his ſervants: the fire ſtill retained its property of burning, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:172634:15"/> yet could not burne them: the power and <note n="c" place="margin">Impoſſibile eſt propria per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecta vel ad momentum temporis ſuis ſubjectis ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri. <hi>Keckerman log. lib. 1.</hi> Nam ſi urendi vis ab igne eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet ſublata, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculum planè nullum a Deo fai. Editum; quid enim mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculi ſit eam rem non urere, quae non poſſit urere? Non ergò in tollendâ ab igne urendi facultate mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum conſiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, ſed in eo quod cum vim urendi maxima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ignis iſte Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonicus obtine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, vis ills fuit divinitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita, ne ſe exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reret, ut quidem ſtatim poſt exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruit abſumens eos qui in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacem eandem inijciebantur. <hi>Kecker. ibid.</hi>
               </note> property of burning was not taken from the fire, for then it had been no miracle: what miracle is it for that thing not to burne which cannot burne? The miracle therefore did not conſiſt in taking away the naturall power of burning from the fire, but in this that when the fire had the grateſt heat and power of burning, yet it could not burne them: The fire had its full power and property to burne, but could not exerciſe it: what an honour was it to walke ſafe in the midſt of the fire? How did God magnify them, that they ſhould be in the fire and yet be ſafe from the fire? the fire doth not kill them but kiſſe them: the fire doth not conſume them, but court them; and denies it ſelf, to give them courteous entertainment: they walke in the fire as in a pleaſant aire: what honours are theſe put upon poor creatures! they were bound hand and foot, when they were caſt into the fire, and yet <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> ſees them walk: the fire had heat to burne their bonds, but not power to touch their bodies: Had they miſt this opportunity of ſuffering they had miſſed of this honour.</p>
            <p>3 Their ſuffering was the Churches honour and advantage: it won great reſpect and honour to the Jewiſh Church and Religion: <hi>Neluchadnezzar</hi> makes a Decree that no people ſhall ſpeake any thing amiſſe of the God of <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach</hi> and <hi>Abednego:</hi> Now their God comes into requeſt with the King himſelfe, and their deliverance flying abroad upon the wing of fame, makes their God famous, and their Religion fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and their people the Jews famous: How many taunts and deriſions caſt daily at the Jewes for their worſhip, were ſuppreſſed by the ſeverity of this Law? Without doubt this D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cree was of ſpeciall uſe for the comfort of the Jewes, they had a ſweet, calme, and Halcion time of peace and ſerenity upon it; Ah! What honour and advantage brought they to the Church by taking this opportunity of ſuffering?</p>
            <p>4 And did not their ſuffering and their deliverance (think yee) ſtrengthen the weak faith of their diſtreſſed brethren the poor Jews? Did it not inſpire them with corage, &amp; root them deeper in the love of their Religion? How many <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Chaldeans</hi> might this great miracle of deliverance worke home to the true God? Surely <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> Decree made the learning of God famous among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> a ſpeciall helpe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:172634:15"/> to converſion; as we may ſee in the three Magi or wiſe<note place="margin">Matth. 2.</note> men.</p>
            <p>Ah my beloved! your ſufferings may be the converſion of others: How willing would we be to preach a Sermon if we knew it would be the converſion of ſome Soul? Let me tel you that thy ſuffering for Chriſt may be the beſt Sermon that ever thou preacheſt all thy life long, and win more upon ſouls, then all the Sermons thou didſt preach in all thy life: as we ſay, that to live well is the beſt preaching, I ſay alſo, to ſuffer well is the beſt preaching; To ſuffer for godlineſſe is the moſt powerfull preaching of godlineſſe. He that can ſuffer beſt for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is the beſt preacher of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> the beſt ſufferer is the beſt Preacher.</p>
            <p>Ah you Saints! this way you may all be Preachers: let your lives preach, and let your ſufferings preach <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> looſe not your opportunities of ſuffering.</p>
            <p>5 I am ſure alſo they will increaſe your future glory:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 17.</note> every ſuffering will be a graine put into the ſcale of your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly glory, to make it more weighty: <hi>For our light affliction which is but for a moment, worketh for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory:</hi> Oh! be for ever contented to have fellowſhip with <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in all his ſufferings; It is ſaid that the Saints have grace for grace with <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent alſo to have ſuffering for ſuffering with <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> you ſhall alſo have glory for glory with him: if you have ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ſuffering, you ſhall alſo have glory for glory with him: Ah then! Looſe not your opportunities of ſuffering for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> if you looſe your opportunity of ſuffering, you looſe a part, a beame of your glory, your glory in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven will be ſo much the darker.</p>
            <p>9 You that are young men, that are the twigs and branches of youth, you have bloſſomes of opportunities growing on you, which if you neglect you ſhall never have the like a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: There are opportunities that are married to youth, which if you ſever can never be united againe: you have ſtrength to ſerve Chriſt, which old age hath not: you have yet no cares of the world in your heads to keep out heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contemplations: you are yet ſcarce in the world, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have not much of the world in you: Oh drinke in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, before you drinke in the cares of the world into your
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:172634:16"/> thoughts: Fill your thoughts firſt with God before you fill them with the world; fill your Sayles with the gales of Chriſt, before they are filled with the aery vanities of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: you have a great deale of your time before you, when old men have their time behind them, gone and paſt, and but a little of it left before them.</p>
            <p>10 So there is an opportunity ſometimes to ſave a whole Church, which if we neglect, we may never have the like again: Such an opportunity came before <hi>Heſter,</hi> which if ſhe had not look't it in the face, and embraced it, all the Jewes had been cut off at one blow by <hi>Hamans</hi> policy: He had got the Kings Decree that the thing ſhould be done, <hi>If it pleaſe the King let it be written that they may be deſtroyed, and the King tooke his Ring</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heſter 3. 9, 10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>from off his hand, and gave it unto Haman, and ſaid unto Haman, the ſilver is given unto thee, the people alſo to doe with them as it ſeemeth good to thee:</hi> The ſignet-Ring did repreſent the Kings authority and name; and therefore when one gave his Ring to another he gave his power over to him to doe what he would in his name; as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> took his Ring off from his hand, and put it upon <hi>Joſephs</hi> hand, that <hi>Joſeph</hi> might in the Kings name ſigne Decrees as Viceroy of <hi>Egypt;</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great when he was ſick and lay ſpeechleſſe, and ſaw no hopes of life, took his Ring from his finger, and gave it to <hi>Perdiccas</hi> to ſignifie (as is thought) that 'twas his mind that <hi>Perdiccas</hi> ſhould ſucceed him: So <hi>Haman</hi> had got the Kings Ring to ſigne the fatall Decree, <hi>And letters were ſent by poſt into all the Kings</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 13.</note> 
               <hi>Provinces to deſtroy, to kill and to cauſe to periſh all Jewes both young and old, little children and women in one day:</hi> Here the poor Church was at a dead lift: <hi>Hamans</hi> teeming hopes were at the birth, nay (as it were) betwixt the wombe and the world; and now heres an opportunity (now or never) to ſtep in and ſave the Church: Save Lord, now or never, <hi>Heſter</hi> takes the opportunity, <hi>Who knows ſaith Mordecay to her, whether thou art</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heſter 4. 14.</note> 
               <hi>come to the Kingdome for ſuch a time as this?</hi> Such a time, which carries nothing but death in the wombe of it: Such a time, wherein the Jews, as if all their necks had ſtood upon one ſhoulder, were deſtined to the blow: at this time <hi>Heſter</hi> ſtrangled the deſigne, and ſaved the Church by taking the opportunity, which had ſhe neglected, a thouſand to one ſhe her ſelfe had never eſcaped to have had the like againe.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:172634:16"/>
            <p>11 Sometimes there's an opportunity given to reforme and purge a Land, which if we neglect may never be given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in our dayes, as you may ſee in <hi>Judges,</hi> the firſt and ſecond Chapter; in the firſt Chapter there you ſhall finde that<note place="margin">Judg. 1. 21. 27. 29. 30.</note> 
               <hi>the Children of Benjamin did not drive out the Jebuſites that inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Jeruſalem, but the Jebuſiies did dwell with the children of Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin in Jeruſalem: Neither did Manaſſeh drive out the inhabitants of Bethſhean and her townes, and neither did Ephraim drive out the Canaanites that dwelt in Gezer: and neither did Zebulun drive out the Inhabitants of Kitron, nor the Inhabitants of Nahalol, but the Canaanites dwelt among them, and became Tributaries, and what then?</hi> ſee Judges 2. 1, 2, 3. <hi>An Angel of the Lord came up from Gilgall to Bochim, and ſaid, I made you to goe up out of Egypt, and have brought you into the Land which I ſware unto your Fathers, and I ſaid, I will never breake my Covenant with you, and you ſhall make no league with the Inhabitants of this Land, you ſhall throw downe their Alters, but you have not obeyed my voice [you have not appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended</hi> the ſeaſon and opportunity, what then? tis loſt in your dayes, and in your ſons dayes, for many generations] <hi>For now I will not drive them out from before you:</hi> I have ſaid it; it is now paſt cure, <hi>but they ſhall be as thornes in your ſides, and their gods ſhall be a ſnare unto you, And when the Angel of the Lord ſpake theſe words unto all the children of Iſrael, the people lift up their voice, and wept, &amp; they called the name of that place Bochin,</hi> that is <hi>Weepers:</hi> they wept ſo much, becauſe they had let ſlip their opportunity, but all their floods of teares could not bring back the opportunity again, nor turne the tide: I pray God this be not <hi>Englands</hi> caſe; time was when we had the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to deſtroy the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> Hereſie, Error, Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe out of land: but now the bird of opportunity is fled out of our hand: She hath taken wing, is fled away and gone: and I feare me we ſhall not ſee her againe in our days: the Scepter of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>primum mobile</hi> of all good govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſet him up, and his government right, and he will ſet Stat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s right: till this great wheel be ſet right, all the leſſer are like enough to goe wrong: Ah <hi>England!</hi> I am afraid of<note place="margin">Ezek. 24. 13.</note> that Text concerning thee, <hi>Becauſe I would have purged thee, and thou waſt not purged, thou ſhall not be purged from thy filthineſſe any more, till I have cauſed my fury to reſt upon thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:172634:17"/>
            <p>Let us now make application; And firſt then, </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Neglect not your opportunities of heaven; make the beſt of your ſouls opportunities: looſe not opportunity for (a world: you have a world of opportunities, looſe not one opportunity for a world: O you that have ſouls to ſave, ſave your opportunities: oh your ſoules! oh your ſouls! I am afraid of your ſouls.</p>
            <p>1 you looſe your ſouls, wee Miniſters looſe all our labour, and Chriſt looſeth all his blood that he hath ſhed for your ſoules, and what account can you give to God for ſo much coſt? Moſt of you doe not value your ſouls worth the ſaving: Many a man doth prize his Oxe or his Aſſe more then ſome men prize their ſoules.</p>
            <p>2 The Devils have loſt their opportunities, will you not take warning by the Devils? if you will not take your op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities you will ſhortly be as irrecoverable as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils.</p>
            <p>3 Opportunities ioſt cannot be bought againe for gold: As <hi>Ahab</hi> could not buy <hi>Naboths</hi> Vineyard of him, <hi>Naboth</hi> would take no money for it; ſo opportunities loſt cannot be bought back againe for money; if thou wouldſt bid never ſo high for them, thou canſt not have them upon any price; thou canſt not pray thine opportunities back againe, thou canſt not weep thine opportunities back againe, as you may ſee by <hi>Eſau,</hi> he loſt his opportunity, and <hi>When afterwards he would have inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited<note place="margin">Heb. 12. 17.</note> the bleſſing, he could finde no place of repentance, though he ſought it with tears: Jacob</hi> was no ſooner gone away with the bleſſing, but <hi>Eſau</hi> comes in with hope of the bleſſing, the bleſſing was gone but one minute, and yet cannot be reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</p>
            <p>4 Every opportunity thou looſeſt thou groweſt worſe and worſe: thou art bad to day, if thou looſeſt this opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 6, 7.</note> thou ſhalt be worſe to morrow: as <hi>Cain,</hi> God converſed with him (as it were) to day, <hi>Why art thou wroth? why is thy countenance fallen, if thou doe well, ſhalt thou not be accepted? and if thou doeſt not well ſin lyeth at the door:</hi> but he was not bettered by this opportunity, and preſently he grew worſe upon it,<note place="margin">Verſe 8.</note> for the next thing he did was, <hi>he talked with his brother Abel, and ſlew him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5 Salvation, which theſe opportunities carry in their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:172634:17"/> wombe, is a tranſcendent birth, a bleſſing of the firſt magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude: who would not be ſaved? all things elſe are but ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows and trifles, to this reality called <hi>Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe are the ſons of wiſedome that contend for ſubſtance, for God, for heaven: God is not a thing indifferent, and, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt</hi> is no circumſtance: Honors, eaſe, worldly profits<note place="margin">Iſtae divitiae nec verae ſunt nec veſtrae.</note> and pleaſures, all theſe, theſe I ſay, are in their nature things indifferent, and being compared and put in the ſcale with Chriſt, are leſſe then things indifferent, even toyes, dreames, loſſe, dung, meer nothings, at beſt but fading things, that paſſe away as a picture drawn upon the Ice, which ſoon vaniſheth: They are meer accidents, nay ſeparable accidents, that may be taken from the ſubject without its hurt, a man may ſpare them and yet be happy; but God is the Eſſence of the Soul, the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Entity of our happineſſe. <hi>This is life eternall to know thee</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 17. 3.</note> 
               <hi>the onely true God and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>6 It may be (O Sinner) that art now in thy ſins, it may be this very day, even this particular Sermon, may be thy day, that if thou repent not at this very Sermon thou looſeſt eternall life for ever.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ended the day of grace on the Scribes and Phariſees even in the very Sermon time whilſt Chriſt was preaching to them, they were delivered up to hardneſſe of heart.</p>
            <p>7 In a word, to paſſe by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> carrieth with it the moſt ſurpaſſing wrath: to diſreſpect the offer of mercy<note place="margin">Heb. 2. 3.</note> uſhers in the greateſt miſery. <hi>How ſhall wee eſcape if wee neglect ſo great Salvation.</hi> That is, you ſhall not eſcape ſo, you ſhall not paſſe with an ordinary doome upon you.</p>
            <p>Sinners! opportunity attends you, Chriſt is yours if you'I have him: the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> is at your ſervice, if you will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace him: God ſends up and downe the world to offer Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, hence that phraſe [<hi>my ſalvation is gone forth</hi>] Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy wayts on you, and kneels to you, and does obeyſance to your ſouls; when you are running from it, mercy runs after you to catch you and imbrace you: Ah how long hath free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace ſtood at your doors, waiting your leiſure when you would let her in? yet ſhe cals and knocks againe, you may yet be ſaved, but if you will goe on ſtill, and diſreſpect mercy, it brings the greateſt miſery; The greateſt ſeverity goes along
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:172634:18"/> with the Goſpel: greateſt ſeverity goes along with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt mercy.</p>
            <p>The Goſpel is the greateſt mercy that ever ſaluted the world, and there's the greateſt ſeverity with the Goſpel that ever came with any mercy into the world: Men ſhall be deeper in hell becauſe heaven was offered them, and they would not: All they ſuffer here is but typicall of the wrath to come: here they but ſip of the top of Gods cup, there they muſt drink the dreggs, though it be eternity, to the bottome; a <hi>Sodomite</hi> in Hell ſhall fare better then the refuſer of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> See the 10. <hi>Mat. 14, 15. verſes,</hi> and <hi>Whoſoever ſhall not receive you, nor hear your words, when you depart out of that houſe or City, ſhake off the duſt of your feet; Verily I ſay unto you it ſhall be more tolerable for the land of Sodome and Gomorah in the day of Judgement, then for that City.</hi> Is not here the greateſt ſeverity with the greateſt mercy? So againe in <hi>Mat. 11. 21, 22. Woe unto thee Corazin, woe unto thee Bethſaida, for if the mighty works which were done in you, had been done in Tyre and Sydon, they would have repented long agoe in Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth and aſhes; but I ſay unto you, it ſhall be more tolerable for Tyre and Sydon at the day of Judgement then for you.</hi> Is not here the greateſt ſeverity going along with the greateſt mercy?</p>
            <p>God can better bear any thing then the contempt of his free grace in the offers of mercy.</p>
            <p>More yet; When the Goſpel began to be preached, faith the Text, <hi>Now is the Axe laid to the root of the Tree; Jeſus Chriſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 3. 10.</note> comes with his Basket and his Axe, his Basket togather fruit, his Axe to cut downe the tree if it will not bear fruit; and is not here the greateſt ſeverity with the greateſt mercy? If there were a ſword on <hi>Moſes</hi> thigh, there is an Axe in Chriſts hand. <hi>Now is the Axe laid to the root of the tree</hi> [Now] that is, your opportunity is Now, if you paſſe by this [now] you are gone; for ought I can tell, you are chopt off preſently. Neglect not the preſent [Now] leaſt yee be cut off for ever.</p>
            <p>8 Conſider ſin is your diſhonour! it doth<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mundiliaenim neceſſaria eſt ad hoc, quod mens Deo applicetur, quià mens Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana inquina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ex hoc quod inferioribus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus conjungitur; ſicut quaelibet Res ex immix-tione pejoris ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcit ut argen. turn ex immix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione plumbi.</hi> Aquia. ſum. 22ae. q. 81. ar 8 cup.</note> degrade you. The veſture of mans nature is baſe and beggarly ſince it was patched with ſin: It is a debaſing of the gold to marry it with any mettal of a courſer birth, ſo 'tis a diſhonour to man to match his golden nature (ſo God at firſt made it holy and righteous) I ſay, to match thy golden nature to baſe-borne droſſe, to low-borne ſin, which derives its pedigree from hell.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:172634:18"/>
            <p>None but <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is a fit match for the ſoule of man, take the opportunity then, and make choice of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Eſpouſe thy ſoul to him, and keep the marriage knot invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late with him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 4.</p>
            <p>9 Come in quickly, take the opportunity to come in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> leaſt your ſins (before you are aware) ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen too faſt, and you be cut downe you know not how ſoon Sins<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>De uno pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to enim in ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ud, ex una tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitudine &amp; ſtuhitiâ in ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ruerant.</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Aetas pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentumpejor avis tulit, Hos nequiore, mox daturos pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniem vitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiorem. <hi>Neque tantum a pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ad peccatum, ſed ab errore &amp; ſtuhitiâ ad <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ad inſaniam et corruptionem mentis, ac rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis Everſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem proceditur.</hi> Cocceius, ad 2 Tim. 3.</note> multiply; one ſin will ſhortly multiply into many; they are like circles in a pond, one circle begets another, ſo doth one ſin beget another, a leſſer begets a greater, as in a caſe of ſtaires, one ſtaire is a ſtep to another, ſo every ſin is a ſtaire to helpe up to higher and worſe ſins.</p>
            <p>It is wonderfull to behold the great flames bred out of ſmall ſparks of ſin, how one ſin hatched a greater; ſin is like a whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pool, which firſt ſucks in one part, and then another, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver deſiſts untill it drawes in and plungeth the wholebody.</p>
            <p>10. man may performe duties of Religion after his day of grace is ſet upon him: you thinke that as long as a man per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes duties, and doth many good things; his day of grace is not paſt: My beloved, òbſerve me. A man may come to Church, performe religious duties, doe many good things, have many meltings upon his heart, after his day of grace is paſt and gone: as <hi>Saul</hi> went on in duties of Religion aſwell af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Samuel</hi> had pronounced the Lords doom upon him as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. How many times was he offering ſacrifice to the Lord, after the Prophet had told him that he was a man rejected? How many good ſpeeches came from him? what meltings ſome time fell in upon his ſoule? as if there were hopes of him, and yet a loſt man, his opportunities of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> My ſecond uſe ſhall be, to ſet out unto you the excellency and Majeſty of Gods opportunities, that you may ſtand in awe and reverence of them, and by no means ſlight them or neglect them: Myſteries are dreadfull, we honor them; <hi>There are my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries</hi>
               <note place="margin">Myſteria tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menda.</note> 
               <hi>in Gods opportunities.</hi> My beloved, there are theſe three characters of myſterie and excellency engraven upon Gods op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities; It may be ſome may thinke of and adde more, but I at preſent obſerve three characters of myſterie and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency upon Gods opportunities. Firſt, they are eaſie, Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they are ſudden and unexſpected, Thirdly, ſometimes they come beſide our</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:172634:19"/>
            <p>1 Firſt, Gods opportunities are eaſie, they bring great matters to birth with eaſie travell: they bring hard things to paſſe eaſily: Oh that this were obſerved. In Gods opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie it is an eaſie thing to beleeve, to repent, to ſubdue a ſin, and to overcome a temptation: as it is an eaſie matter for the Ship to go when ſhe hath the winde to fill her ſayls. Every thing is done eaſily in Gods opportunitie, whether it be to ſave a ſoul, or to deſtroy a ſoule: becauſe God in his opportunity makes all things concur and brings circumſtances together to ſtrike up the action ſuddenly you ſhall ſee it.</p>
            <p>1 Firſt, In the ruine of a man, in the deſtruction of a man: when 'tis Gods opportunitie to deſtroy a man, what eaſie way will he make for't? As <hi>Saul,</hi> when Gods time came that he muſt periſh, he ſlew himſelfe, there was no difficulty in the<note place="margin">1 Sam. 31. 4.</note> worke, he fell himſelfe upon his ſword, as the ſtone doth to its center: How eaſily was <hi>Jericho</hi> taken? when the Prieſts blew the Trumpets, and the people ſhouted, the wals fel down flat of themſelves: How eaſily was <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Army de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed in the red Sea? The Sea was divided, and a way made for him, that he might not ſtand upon't, but run voluntary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the womb of death; Oh the efficacy of Gods opportunities! How eaſily did <hi>Goliah</hi> fall, what ſtirres and bluſterings did he act a little before upon the ſtage of pride and boaſting, making a challenge to all <hi>Iſrael?</hi> but when Gods opportunitie comes how eaſily is he ſlaine? And therefore the Scripture ſpeaks this with an Emphaſis. <hi>So</hi> David <hi>prevailed over the Philiſtine with a ſling and with a ſtone, and ſmote the Philiſtine, and ſlew him, but there was no ſword in the hand of</hi> David.</p>
            <p>2 So Gods opportunities worke good for men eaſily, they bring great matters of good to paſſe with no difficulty: when 'tis Gods opportunitie that <hi>David</hi> ſhall take poſſeſſion of his Kingdome, it fals into his mouth (as it were) not onely <hi>Saul,</hi> but all his ſons, (that might ſtand as ſo many ſcreens between <hi>David</hi> and the Crowne) are taken out of the way. The houſe of <hi>Judah,</hi> they of themſelves, come and annoint <hi>David</hi> King o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them. Then <hi>Abner Sauls</hi> Generall of his whole Army, diſpleaſed with <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi> revolts to <hi>David,</hi> and all the Tribes come to <hi>Hebron</hi> to annoint <hi>David</hi> King over <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Do you ſee? this great worke is done to his hand.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:172634:19"/>
            <p>So in Gods opportunities it is an eaſie thing to beleeve and repent, <hi>Act. 16. 14. Luk. 19. 6. 1 Kin.</hi> 19. 20.</p>
            <p>Ah my beloved! the eaſe of beleiving and repenting at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends a peculiar opportunity of Gods owne vouchſafing in which he doth more readily worke then at other times.</p>
            <p>How ſhall I know when 'tis eaſie for me to beleeve and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent?</p>
            <p>1 When the light of the ſpirit doth flaſh into the eye of thy ſoule, then thy worke is eaſie, as when the light of the day doth dart its rayes in at the windows of thy Chamber 'tis eaſie for thee to read a ſmall print. Thus when a light from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven did ſhine upon <hi>Paul,</hi> and ſhine into <hi>Paul,</hi> how eaſie did his worke come off? Lord what wilt thou have me to doe?</p>
            <p>2 When thy heart is made combuſtible and ready to take fire: as when the tinder is dry 'tis eaſie to light a candle, the leaſt ſparke that fals on it takes fire, and when the fire is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtible, it is an eaſie matter to kindle a fire, it burnes preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: So when thy heart is ſoftned it eaſily takes the impreſſion of the ſeale upon it, and when thy thoughts are ſtir'd up and made combuſtible, 'tis an eaſie matter to kindle them into a fire of repentance, as in the <hi>Acts,</hi> when they were pricked in<note place="margin">Act. 2.</note> the heart, they ſaid, Men and brethren what ſhall wee doe? repent (ſaith <hi>Peter</hi>) and they took preſently.</p>
            <p>3 When thine affections and deſires are upon the wheel, then any worke is eaſie, as when a load is upon the wheel 'tis drawne eaſily, whereas if you ſhould goe about to lug it along upon the ground it comes on heavily; and therefore the Lord purſuing <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> took off his Chariot wheels, and they drave on heavily: So when God puts thine affections upon the wheel, and ſets them a going, then 'tis eaſie for thee to doe great matters, and therefore obſerve thine opportunity.</p>
            <p>2 Gods opportunities are ſudden and unexpected: they come upon us without preparation; God doth not ſend us word before hand, when he will viſit us and come to us, as ſometimes we ſend to a friend that we will dine with him, or ſpeake with him at ſuch an howre; but Gods opportunities come ſuddenly upon us in the twinkling of an eye, before we be aware, when we know nothing of it, and the ſpirit ruſheth in upon a man, and gives him no notice before hand, Thus Chriſt came and called <hi>Matthew</hi> [follow me] on a ſudden,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:172634:20"/> whilſt he was ſitting at the receipt of Cuſtome, <hi>And he aroſe and followed him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some poor ſoules have ſent up many a prayer to heaven for aſſurance, and it hath not come, and they poor creatures have thought that God hath not regarded them all the while, and then, on a ſudden, aſſurance hath come when they look't not for it: Ah dear father, how many mercies from thee have come to us uninvited! thy preventing grace and mercy doth alwayes viſit us uninvited: we ſend not for it, it comes freely to us.</p>
            <p>3 Gods opportunities come beſides our intention, they come ſometimes when we aime not at them: We ſtumble up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on heaven, when we are ſeeking ſomething elſe; as a man that digged in his garden only to ſet roots and plants, and found a pot of gold there; and as <hi>Saul</hi> went to <hi>Samuel</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire for his Fathers Aſſes, and found a Kingdome. This was beſides his intention, he ſought one thing and found another, his poor Aſſes were in his intention, but a Crowne was the object he met with in execution. Oh the miſteries of opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity! 'Tis ſo many times in the matters of heaven, <hi>I am found ſaith God of them that ſought me not.</hi> Many a ſoul findes Heaven beſides his intention: How ſtrangely doe ſome meet with a Commiſſion? they meet with heaven and grace by acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent (as it were) they goe to a place onely to ſeek health or food, ſomething for the body, and there they light upon (beſides their intention) ſalvation for their ſoules, as the lame man ſeeing <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> asked an almes, there was all his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and met with a cure both of body and ſoule: and the woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> came to the Well for water, and there found a Chriſt. It was an accident to her to meet Chriſt there: Gods opportunity comes upon her beſides her intention: Ah gracious God! that ſhe ſhould come for water that very houre when Chriſt was there, not before nor after, but that very houre when Chriſt is there: ſhee came for water which was but puddle, and found a Spring of life; So the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that took <hi>Jonah</hi> into their Ship, they received him onely<note place="margin">Jonah 1. 3.</note> for the fare, he payd them, that was all their intention, their fare and pay for carriage was all their aime, but they met with a better fare, converſion to the true God, <hi>verſe 16. Then the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n (h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y were Heathens) feared the Lord exceedingly, and offered
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:172634:20"/> a ſacrifice to the Lord</hi> [that is, to the true God, not to Neptune but to the Lord] <hi>and made vowes,</hi> So <hi>Moſes</hi> went to mount <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reb</hi> onely to keep his Fathers ſheep, but there he met with God in the burning buſh. Thus you ſee Gods opportunities are cloathed with ſtately robes of myſtery upon them, behold them therefore with holy feare and reverence.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> My third uſe ſhall give the meeting to tender ſouls, who will be ready from the breaſts of this doctrine to ſuck in fears and ſcruples, giving up their opportunities for gone: If this be ſo, then we have loſt our opportunities; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>1</label> I am an old ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and have ſtood it out all my dayes hitherto againſt Jeſus Chriſt, he hath often called me, and I have often refuſed him.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Yet thou art not in hell, thou art yet on this ſide the grave: O praiſe mercy and free grace, that thou art not yet in the center of hell: thou canſt not ſay that the oyle of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity is ſpent, as long as thou haſt a veſſel more, a day, or year yet more left to receive it; the widdows oyle ran ſtill as long as there was a veſſell to receive it: Thou canſt not ſay that opportunity is done, till life be done: God hath many opportunities, though many are loſt, yet all are not paſt. Thou ſayſt thou haſt loſt ſome opportunities, but God hath many opportunities in ſtore: Indeed, if God had but one op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity for thee and no more, thou wert gone as <hi>Eſau</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Jacob, Haſt thou but one bleſſing oh my Father?</hi> But God<note place="margin">Gen. 27. 38.</note> hath many bleſſings, he hath many mercies, and therefore ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny opportunities for loſt ſoules, he doth not give off for many denyals; after many refuſalls God comes on again, and woes afreſh: he hath a treaſury of opportunities, a quiver full of opportunities, and if one arrow of mercy be ſpent, if more arrows of opportunitie be loſt, and throwne away upon thee, he hath more yet to ſhoot at thee, and more yet; Oh that God would now draw out an arrow of converſion, and hit thy ſoule with it! What though God hath bent his bow, and ſhot many an arrow, many a Sermon at thee, and miſſed? Yet he will ſhoot againe, he can ſhoot and hit, he is rich in mercies, and therefore rich in opportunities: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> Oh, but I have left my firſt love; I have abated in my flame of love to God, and his word, and the power of godlineſſe; and is my opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie yet before me to recover? is it not loſt? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> No, it is not loſt,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:172634:21"/> thine opportunity yet is not gone, as you may ſee in <hi>Revel. 2. 4. 5. Nevertheleſſe I have ſomewhat againſt thee, becauſe thou haſt left thy firſt love.</hi> Obſerve, thou that haſt decayed in the heat of thy firſt love, God hath ſomewhat againſt thee, he hath a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell with thee, and therefore awake with all ſpeed, for God hath ſomewhat againſt thee, but yet thine opportunity is not gone: for ſaith God in the next words; <hi>Remember therefore whence thou art fallen, and repent, and doe thy firſt works,</hi> there's yet opportunity that ſhines on thee, the Sun is not yet ſett, though it be going downe: <hi>and if thou wilt remember whence thou art fallen, and repent,</hi> and make haſte to riſe, God will rather make the Sun to ſtand ſtill (as he did in <hi>Joſhuahs</hi> time) The Sun of opportunity ſhall rather ſtand ſtill in the orbe of time, then that thou ſhalt looſe thy ſoul, therefore looke about thee.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> Oh but I am growne luke-warme in religion, which is the worſt temper of all the reſt, I care not which end goes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> Chriſt will afford thee opportunities yet, as you may ſee in the Church of <hi>Laodicea, Rev. 3. 15. I know thy workes [I know what they are and utterly diſlike them] thou art neither hot nor cold,</hi> Thou art neither an open enemy, nor yet truly zealous of my Goſpel, verſe 16. <hi>Therefore becauſe thou art luke-warm I will ſpew thee out of my mouth:</hi> as tepid and luke-warme water doth provoke the ſtomack to ſpew it out againe: So will I (ſaith God) ſpew thee and thy profeſſion out, it is ſo loathſome to me. Obſerve (thou luke-warme Chriſtian) thou art in a ſad and dangerous condition, God cannot bear with thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion long, as the ſtomack cannot hold luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme water long within it, yet thine opportunities are not yet gone, for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Behold I ſtand at the door, and knock, if any man hear</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 20.</note> 
               <hi>my voice, and open the door, I will come in unto him, and ſup with him and he with me;</hi> though thou art luke-warme and deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt with thy profeſſion to be ſpewed out of my mouth, <hi>yet I ſtand at the door and knock:</hi> Chriſt was going. (O obſerve thou luke-warme Chriſtian, and therefore ſaith he) <hi>I ſtand at the door and knock,</hi> but (ſaith hee) l'le pauſe a while before I goe, l'le ſtay a little and then goe, I am unwilling to leave thee yet, though thou ſhut me out I will not yet be gone, though the door be lockt againſt me, yet I'le knock a while; for this phraſe ſhewes that Chriſt was ſtayed from entring in preſently
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:172634:21"/> the doors being ſhut againſt him; yet he would ſtand there waiting, though you be all aſleep within, yet I will ſee whether I can knock you up: The opportunitie waited ſtill upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>4</label> But God ſeems to have caſt me off into a Sea of ſadneſſe and deſertion: he hath throwne me over Ship-board out of his preſence into a depth of deſpaire; I ſinke, I ſinke under his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, I feare me I ſhall never recover, I am ſo drowned in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean of his frownes, his waves are gone over my Soule.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> A man may thinke himſelfe gone, and yet his opportunitie not gone, he may thinke himſelf paſt helpe, and yet his oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity not paſt; he may ſay, God hath caſt me off, I ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver recover more, never ſee the face of God more, and yet op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity ſhew its face againe, and ſmiles upon him. I will give you a ſtrange inſtance, <hi>Jonah</hi> in the Whales belly, he had ſinned, highly againſt the Lord, like a Runagate who fled from his Maſters ſervice, and when he was upon the Sea, a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt purſueth him, which would not give him over; a Lot to diſcover the malefactor is caſt, and it fals upon <hi>Jonas;</hi> The Marriners they caſt him over Ship-board: here was a fearfull caſe, to bee caſt over Shipp-board with a guilty conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: how did he fall into the Sea, that had a Sea of terror in him? Well; he is caſt in, and a Whale ſwallows him, in whoſe belly he is lodged for three dayes and three nights, after ſuch a manner as was never heard of before: how perplexed was his ſtate think you? a man drowned and not drowned; devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but not digeſted; alive, but yet as dead; ah what a dying ſoul had he in the living Fiſh! expecting every minute the fearefull diſſolution of his Soul from his body; for he was under horror of conſcience, now lying on him for his ſin, and dreadfull conflict of Spirit, as if God had forſaken him, and given ſentence on him, for you ſhall read, ſome ſuch were his expreſſions, <hi>Thou haſt caſt me into the deep,</hi> that is, the<note place="margin">Jonah 2. 3, 4.</note> Sea; <hi>then I ſaid, I am caſt out of thy ſight, my Soul fainted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me.</hi> Here <hi>Jonah</hi> thought his opportunity was gone, but the Whale brings him ſafe to the ſhore, the Whales belly was a place of ſafety, a ſanctuary to him, had not the Whale recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him, he might have been drowned, for he could not ſwim to the ſhore. Ah thou poor dejected ſoul! know that God can be angry, and yet love thee; he can throw thee into the belly of deſpaire, and make thee live in it, as the child doth in the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:172634:22"/> wombe, The Mothers belly is the Babes Sanctuary, the child lyes ſafe in the womb, ſo ſhalt thou lye ſafe in the belly of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, God will make the belly or womb of deſpair to travel in birth till thou art delivered, and therefore doe as <hi>Jonah</hi> did, beleeve in the midſt of deſpaire, pray unto the Lord, cry unto him out of the whales belly, <hi>Out of the belly of hell</hi> (ſaith<note place="margin">Jonah 2. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Jonah) I cryed and thou heardeſt my voice;</hi> Ah, bleſſed word! God will hear thee when thou art at the worſt; if thou couldſt pray in hell, and repent in hell, wert thou in hell, if thou couldſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve there, God would hear thee there; a ſweet word to a deſpairing ſoule: <hi>Jonah</hi> in the Whales belly ſaid, <hi>Yet I will look againe toward thy holy Temple;</hi> God will give thee leave to look up to him though thou art in the bottome of deſtruction: <hi>I am caſt out of thy ſight</hi> (ſaid <hi>Jonah) yet I will looke againe toward thy holy Temple?</hi> A ſoul is never ſo forſaken of God but he may look up to his God; though thou art caſt out of his ſight, yet he will give thee leave to look upon him: ah thou for ſaken ſoul! a look from thee will pierce his boſom, a mournfull look from the child wounds the breaſt of the angry father; though the child dares not ſend out a word, yet a mournfull and longing look conquers his Fathers heart: Art thou forſaken of God? yet thine opportunity is not gone, dart a look upon him, if thou canſt not pray to him, yet look upon him: God lookes to ſee whether thou wilt look upon him: he waits to be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious,<note place="margin">Iſa. 30. 18.</note> thou waiteſt to be comforted, he waits to comfort thee.</p>
            <p>5 Mans extremity is Gods opportunity: when thou art moſt ready to periſh, then is God moſt ready to ſave: God or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily doth not ſave in danger, but in extremity of danger; when 'tis at the worſt with thee, then 'tis Gods opportunity to help thee, as the woman that had the bloody iſſue, her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity was Chriſts opportunity; She had a waſting diſeaſe upon her, and time added to it; twelve long years had ſhe wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and languiſhed under it; beſides the tediouſneſſe, her diſeaſe muſt needs get head by continuance, yet more to mend the matter, poverty (which is another diſeaſe) was ſuper-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to her ſickneſſe (ſhe had ſpent all that ſhe had upon Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians) her extremity now ſwels great, ſhe hath two evils at once upon her, two unſuffererable evils, though ſhe were ſick, yet her wealth (as long as ſhe had it) would have maintained
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:172634:22"/> and ſuccoured her in her ſickneſſe, but now want doth pinch her no leſſe then her diſtemper, and helps to make her perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſerable: ſhe is now perfectly miſerable, weak and ſick, and nothing to refreſh her in her weakneſſe: had ſhe ſpent all and gained her health it had been well enough, but alas, ſhe hath beggered her ſelfe, undone her ſtate, and her body; never the better, her mony was waſted not her diſeaſe. Now her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity is at the height, what then? her extremity is Chriſts opportunity; when her caſe is moſt deſparate ſhe is healed.<note place="margin">1 Kings 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>If I can but touch the hemme of his garment I ſhall be whole.</hi> So the widdow of <hi>Sarepta; Elijah</hi> ſent to her by God to be ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by her: when he comes he ſuſtaines her, ſhe is ſuſtained by him: for when he comes and asks her food, <hi>bring me I pray thee a morſell of bread in thine hand,</hi> ſhe tells him, <hi>as the Lord thy God liveth, I have not a Cake, but an handfull of meal in a barrell, and a little oyle in a Cruiſe, and behold I am gathering two ſticks, that I may goe in and dreſſe it for me and my Son, that we may eat it and dye.</hi> She was now upon the borders of extremity: It was high time for the Lord to ſend the Prophet to her, for (poor Soul) ſhe was now making her laſt meal; after one meane morſell ſhe was yeelding her ſelfe over to death; ſhe was now going to eat her laſt, that ſhe might dye: and what then? truly her extremity was Gods opportunity, <hi>Feare not ſaid Elijah to her, goe and doe as thou haſt ſaid; make me a little Cake firſt, and bring it to me, and after make for thee and thy ſon; for thus ſaith the Lord God of Iſrael, the Barrel of meal ſhall not waſte, neither ſhall the Cruiſe of oyle faile untill the day that the Lord ſendeth raine upon the earth.</hi> What a ſhowre of comfort was here? ſhe was going to eat her laſt and dye, and God ſends the Prophet to her to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for her the whole famine: How opportunely doth God provide ſuccour to our diſtreſſes! It is his glory to helpe at a pinch, to begin where wee have given over, that his mercy may be ſo much the more welcome by how much it is the leſſe look't for.</p>
            <p>6 Though I have loſt time, yet (ſay) Lord thou haſt not loſt time, thou wert before all time, and canſt ſet time yet before me: My loſſe of time doth not put thee to a loſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> 7 But wil God be a looſer by me? I have loſt him abundance of glory which I might have done him, had I improved my opportunities: In my looſing my opportunities, God hath loſt a great deal of his glory.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:172634:23"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> God will be content to ſit downe by the loſſe if thou wilt but come in now: Oh tranſcendent mercy! he will looſe a great part of his glory rather then looſe thy ſoul, for he knows he can bear the loſſe better then thou canſt.</p>
            <p>2 What he looſeth of his glory by the one way, he gaines another way, in pardoning of thee; he counts it his glory to pardon thee: as the Holy Ghoſt, ſaith, <hi>It is a mans glory to paſſe over a tranſgreſſion.</hi> In pardoning the ſins thou haſt lived in for a time, he will gaine glory to himſelfe beyond all time; Thou haſt ſinned againſt him ſome years, and ſo he hath loſt his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry<note place="margin">Pro. 19. 11.</note> by thee for ſome years, but if he pardon thee thou wilt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify him (wilt thou not?) for ever.</p>
            <p>3 What ever glory thou haſt loſt him, he hath it all made up in Jeſus Chriſt: come in now then and ſerve him cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Chriſt, doe more for him in a little time, then thou haſt done againſt him in a long time.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> 8 But I have prayed long, and waited a great while, and the Lord doth not hear nor anſwer me, and therefore my op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity is paſt; when God hath done hearing prayer, the opportunity is paſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> This doth not argue that thine opportunity is gone, but that God doth not anſwer thee as ſoon as thou askeſt: Thine opportunity is not paſt, but onely God takes his leaſure to hear thee when he pleaſeth: the opportunity is not paſt, but God makes thee ſtay a while before he anſwers: the Lord doth not always time his anſwers to the ſwiftneſſe of our expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>2 Gods delayes ſhould make thee ſet on him with greater ſtrength, and his putting thee off ſhould make thee put on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh with ſtronger violence; as the cold weather makes the fire burne hotter, ſo Gods ſlackneſſe ſhould make thee more hot and earneſt in prayer; and (by an holy Antiperiſtaſis) be kindled from his coldneſſe: Thus 'tis with the men of the world, when <hi>Balak</hi> ſent meſſengers unto <hi>Balaam</hi> to come unto him, and curſe the people <hi>Iſrael; Balaam</hi> denyed him, and ſent him word back, that God would not give him leave to come: what then? ſayth the Text, <hi>Balak ſent againe certaine Princes more, and more honorable then they,</hi> ſo little is <hi>Balak</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged<note place="margin">Numb. 22. 15.</note> with one refuſall, that he ſent ſo much the ſtronger meſſage, <hi>More Princes and more honorable;</hi> ah that we could be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:172634:23"/> ſo importunate for our good, and with our God! a denyall doth but whet the deſires of vehement Suitors: Why are yee faint in ſpirituall things, when yee are not denyed but delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? doth God put the off? ſend up more prayers, and more honorable againe to him.</p>
            <p>3 And therefore when after much ſeeking thou meeteſt not with peace and aſſurance, do not ſay thine opportunity is paſt, but rather ſay, thine opportunity is not yet come, or thine<note place="margin">Heb. 10. 37.</note> opportunity is yet to come, <hi>For yet a little time, and he that ſhall come will come, and will not tarry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How ſhall I know mine opportunity is yet to come?<note place="margin">How ſhall I know mine opportunity is yet to come? Hab. 2. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>1 When thou liveſt in expectation when thou ſtandeſt upon thy watch tower to ſee what he will ſay unto thee.</p>
            <p>2 When thou waiteſt in the uſe of means, when thou wilt not leave the uſe of means: when thou ſtickeſt by the poole of <hi>Betheſda</hi> as the lame man did, that had a diſeaſe eight and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years, there he came to be healed, but he was ſtill prevented, becauſe when he was going downe into the water, another al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſtept downe before him; yet there he ſtayed, he knew there was the place and means of healing, and from thence he would not goe; if he would lye any where he would lye there: and was his opportunity loſt, though he had waited long, and been put by often? (this is the very doubt) No ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: Chriſt viſits him at laſt, there he waited in the uſe of meanes, and rather then fail he ſhall be healed without means.</p>
            <p>3 When the Fig-tree bloſſomes, then thine opportunity is yet to come, nay 'tis at hand: when any bloſſomes of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe any buds and beginnings of a worke appear, any brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things of ſoul in thee after Chriſt, then thine opportunity is at hand; as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Learne a Parable of the Fig-tree, when his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 24. 32.</note> 
               <hi>branch is yet tender and putteth forth leaves, know that Summer is nigh;</hi> and therefore cheriſh every bloſſome of grace, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo tender in thee. Let not a <hi>May</hi>-froſt nip them: <hi>Be yee lift up yee everlaſting doores, and the King of glory ſhall come in:</hi> When your doors, your ſouls begin to lift up themſelves ever ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle after Chriſt, the King of glory is comming in.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>9</label> But you bid us take the opportunity, and come in now to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and beleeve in him and repent, and come out of ſin: alas you bid us doe what we cannot doe, we cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, nor repent, nor come out of ſin: or come to Jeſus Chriſt of our ſelves.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:172634:24"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> You are to beleeve that you cannot beleeve of your ſelfe, or repent of your ſelfe, or come out of ſin by your own ſtrength: and you are not therefore the farther from Chriſt, in that you are ſo farr from your ſelves, nay you are neerer to Jeſus Chriſt. The farther you goe out of your ſelves, and out of your owne ſtrength, the neerer you are gone to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> when you ſeriouſly and feelingly ſay that you cannot beleeve of your ſelves, This is the firſt ſeed of faith, I ſay to beleeve that you cannot beleeve of your ſelves is the firſt ſeed of faith: you muſt firſt beleeve your owne weakneſſe, that you may have power from Chriſt to beleeve in Chriſt: Is there ever a poor ſoul then in this Congregation, that cryes out, I cannot come out of ſin of my ſelfe? this is the firſt worke and ſtep unto <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> to receive ſtrength from him to come out of ſin: doſt thou ſay thou canſt not come out of ſin of thy ſelf? Now thou art the farther from thy ſelfe, and the neerer to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> They whom Chriſt helps, he makes them firſt ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves helpleſſe; <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> gives ſtrength to them, whom he makes to ſee their owne nothingneſſe: they that ſay they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not beleeve, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is in the way to make them beleeve: They that ſay Lord I cannot overcome my ſin, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 9.</note> their Conquerour for them; thy nothingneſſe ſhall ſet out his power, <hi>for my ſtrength</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is made perfect in weaknes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 And againe, whereas thou ſayeſt, I bid thee doe what thou canſt not doe, thou canſt not repent, nor come out of ſin of thy ſelfe, I anſwer and tell thee, <hi>God offers his hand with thee to the worke,</hi> he does not onely offer thee worke to doe, but he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers his hand with thee to the worke: while he bids thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, his hand ſhall be with thee to make thee beleeve: This is the excellency and kindneſſe of the Covenant of grace, when the Goſpel bids thee leave ſin, it puts in thee a new nature, that is contrary to ſin, to hate it more then hell; If a man (to whom thou oweſt ſo much) bid thee pay him a thouſand pounds, and give thee the thouſand pounds in thy hand to pay him, now it is eaſie. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in the Goſpel does not onely ſay to thee, pay me what thou oweſt mee. I am thy Saviour, beleeve in me, I come downe from heaven to dye for thee, come out of ſin to ſerve me; I bought thee with a price, pay me downe thy ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lfe, thy ſervice which thou oweſt me. I ſay Jeſus Chriſt doth not onely thus bid thee (poor ſinner) beleeve in him, and come out of ſin, but he is ready to give thee his grace and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:172634:24"/> ſtrength to make payment. <hi>A new heart will I give thee, and a new ſpirit will I put into thee:</hi> and therefore doe not ſay abſolutely, I cannot beleeve, or I cannot come out of ſin, for Jeſus Chriſt is ready to give thee thy thouſand pounds thou oweſt him, that thou mayſt pay him out of his owne ſtock; that thou mayſt beleeve out of his treaſury, that thou mayſt come out of ſin by his grace and mercy; The Lord Jeſus offers his hand with thee to the work: as <hi>Bernard</hi> tels us of Pope <hi>Eugenius,</hi> that meeting with a poor but honeſt Biſhop, he ſecretly gave him certaine Jewels wherewith he might preſent him: So Jeſus Chriſt will give thee the Jewels of faith and repentance where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou mayſt preſent him: If God did not furniſh us, we ſhould have nothing wherewith to honour him: The Father that gave thee Chriſt wil give thee faith to receive Jeſus Chriſt, and Jeſus Chriſt that gave thee himſelfe, will give thee his ſpirit to draw thee to himſelfe.<note place="margin">Ver. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>How ſhall we know our opportunities?</p>
            <p>I will lay downe but two things before you.</p>
            <p>1 Conſult with the Lord: as it is ſaid of the children of Iſrael, that when the Gibeonites deceived them with a wile, and they ſpared their lives, whom they ſhould have deſtroyed, the Text ſaith, <hi>They asked not counſell at the mouth of the Lord;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſhua 9. 14.</note> they had an opportunity here put into their hands to deſtroy the Gibeonites, but they miſſed it, becauſe they did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with the Lord: do but compare the ſeventh ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe with the fourteenth, and you ſhall ſee how right a man may g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe of a thing ſometimes, and yet want a clear light and diſcovery of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe he doth not adviſe with the Lord; in the ſeventh verſe, <hi>Said the men of Iſrael to the Hivites, peradventure you dwell amongſt us, and how ſhall we make league with you?</hi> here the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites did gueſſe aright, it was paſt (a peradventure) for they did live among them; and therefore could not make a league with them: How right did they hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? how true was their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture? Now the lock of opportunity was before them, they might have laid hold upon it, but they were in the darke, and walkt in a cloud, not knowing who the Gibeonites were, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they asked not counſell at the mouth of the Lord,</hi> (that is) by the high Prieſt putting on the breaſt-plate of judgement wherein was the Urim and Thummim) ſo the reaſon why we know not our opportunities is becauſe we conſult not with
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:172634:25"/> the Lord: as he is the maker of time, ſo he is the revealer of time unto us: Nay, Gods will to worke at ſuch a time, is that which makes an opportunity, as ſuppoſe a man in a curious Apple-tree or Plumb-tree; your opportunity to gether, and carry away fruit is, when it is his will to ſhake the tree, before or after is no opportunity: you may walke, and watch about the tree, when he will ſhake downe the fruit, but when he hath done ſhaking, your opportunity is done. So the Lord, who is the husbandman of his Church, he hath among all his other<note place="margin">Joh. 15. 1. 1 Cor. 3. 9.</note> trees, planted the tree of time, and he himſelfe ſits upon the top of the tree (as the God of time, the diſpoſer of time) and when it is his will to ſhake the tree, then is your opportunity: So that if you would know your opportunities you muſt conſult with the Lord, Lord, when wilt thou ſhake thy tree? when wilt thou drop downe the fruit, that I may gather into my lap?</p>
            <p>2 If you would not looſe any opportunity, apprehend e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one; as <hi>Abraham</hi> by entertaining ſtrangers, entertained Angels unawares: As a man that keeps an Inne, by enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining all travellers that come, oftentimes entertaines a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-man, or a Prince; So if thou entertaine all opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that come, thou ſhalt at laſt entertaine the noble oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, the Angel opportunity, the Prince of opportunities, the Soul-ſaving opportunity; a thouſand to one thou ſhalt entertain Chriſt at laſt; as the Inne at <hi>Bethlem</hi> that entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all paſſengers, entertained Chriſt himſelf there.</p>
            <p>Sinners, I told you before, that God will at one hour or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther come with a caſting command; one command that ſhall have the caſting voice; that if you obey not then, mercy will ſhut up ſhop, and trade with you no more, but give you up for ever; and therefore I ſay now if you would not looſe any opportunity, take every opportunity.</p>
            <p>And now give my diſcourſe leave to caſt ſome beams of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon that worthy Gentleman whom God hath taken from us: 'Tis our duty to ſpeak ſomething of him: Though we bury his body, yet 'tis not fit we ſhould bury his worth in a grave of ſilence and oblivion, and truly (my beloved) I doe not thinke yee can bury the ſweet remembrance of him; Hee will live a long time after his death, though he be dead, yet he cannot dye, his name cannot expire ſo ſoon: Oh! that what good was in him might live after him to gives us example:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:172634:25"/> Hee was an exemplary patterne; when hee's laid in this grave hee'l live above the grave, the ſweet ſmelling ſpices of his lovely life and converſation will imbalme him, and keep him unperiſht in your thoughts many years. I need not blazon his coat of arms (you may ſee them upon the ſable hearſe) the worth of his deſcent or luſtre of his family, <hi>Et genus &amp; proavos &amp; quae not fecimus ipſi;</hi> you did all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him and know him, Mr. <hi>Walcot</hi> of <hi>Walcot:</hi> beſides that he was honored with the office of Juſtice of Peace in his Country, &amp; truly I thinke the office in ſome meaſure received honour from him, for he adorned it with his vertues: he moved in that ſphear for many years together, in which place both he and that worthy Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman,<note place="margin">And once a Member of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</note> now with the Lord, M. <hi>Rich, More</hi> of <hi>Linley</hi> Eſq. (whom for honors ſake I cannot but revive and mention) In which place I ſay (you all know) how they two uniting their beames together, refreſhed your countrey with the warmth of their influence; exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Juſtice, relieving the poor, placing Orphans, puniſhing of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendors, ſuppreſſing the prophanation of Sabbaths, countenancing the godly, ſupporting the courſe of godlineſſe and religion, hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and backing the faithfull Miniſters of God. I well remember thoſe times, I ſpeak but what yee all know.</p>
            <p>He was alſo (having intereſt in ſo many Churches) as great an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument (I think) as any in the Countrey, to propagate the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and preaching of the word.</p>
            <p>That excellent man of God Mr. <hi>Pierſon</hi> of <hi>Brompton Bryan</hi> had a large room in this Gentlemans heart, and kindled that pious flame in him: and when M. <hi>Pierſon</hi> dyed, this flame dyed not in this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemans breaſt, till the oyle of his life waſted; ſurely 'twas a true worke, it laſted in him.</p>
            <p>It was his care to get as godly Miniſters, and able as he could; and how dear were his Miniſters to him? I dare ſay, next to his wife and children, Firſt, he was a father to them: they were to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſee the flock, and truly he would over-ſee them that they ſhould want nothing according to his ability. When they came to viſit him, his common quxre was, Is it comfortable with you? do you want? tell me if you doe, let me know it? I would not have you diſcouraged, nor goe on drooping in Gods work. I ſpeak but truth themſelves are witneſſes.</p>
            <p>He was a mirrour and example of temperance to all the Gentry in the countrey.</p>
            <p>I know no greater infirmity did lye upon him then timerouſnes, he had not that height of maſculine ſpirit w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> dwelt in ſome men:</p>
            <p>But my beloved, he that is without ſin among you let him caſt the firſt ſtone.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:172634:26"/> He was as meek as a Lamb: a child might reprove him; an inferiour might boldly tell him where (he thought) he went awry. I never found any like him in this, he would ever love a man for it.</p>
            <p>As for Covetouſnes, I dare ſay he was not much acquainted with it; for 1 when he had an opportunity to exerciſe covetouſneſſe in the diſpoſure of the Vicarage of <hi>Clun,</hi> he gave it me as freely as the Sun ſhines upon me in the day time; he was no mercenary Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron. 2 Covetouſnes and mercy never dwell together; a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous man cannot be a mercifull man; but he was a man made up of pity and mercy to the poor; I ſpeak but what you all know; the bellies of the hungry, and the backs of the naked did every yeare proclaim his bounty and charity. 3 Beſides a covetous liver is no free giver in ſecret: a covetous man, when he gives, will cauſe his gifts to run in a viſible channel to be ſeen of men; but (to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) he was a ſecret and hidden reliever of godly widdows and others that were in want; he refreſht their bowels with his hid trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: he would ſend to know their indigencies and their ſtraits; they need not ſent to him, he would ſend to them. 4 Yet more, a covetous man is not a cheerfull man under loſſes: but he was ſweet and ſmiling under all his loſſes. 'Tis well knowne, theſe times ſrown'd upon him, and made him a great looſer, yet he had a moſt compoſed and contented heart under them, with a great deal of acquieſcence in God. 5 Beſides, no man knew the dimenſions of his eſtate better then himſelf, ſo that knowing what I now do know, I admire at his conſtant liberality.</p>
            <p>He was of a meek ſpirit, wonderful free from the tang of revenge; I know no man had ſuch a rare art of forgiving injuries as he had: if any had ſpoke ill of him, or done ill to him, he would be ſilent, &amp; paſſe it by with this, <hi>They are but men, they ſhew themſelves to be men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was a pattern of patience under affliction; Surely there was much worth in this Gentleman, your faces ſpeak ſuch ſadneſſe for his loſſe and departure; Methinks I read a ſad love—and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſadneſſe written upon your faces for him.</p>
            <p>It may be ſome may think, that in ſetting out his graces and his works, that I place ſome merit in theſe things: No, I doe not, and therefore let me tell you, that when he was like to dye before, (for now God took him ſuddenly) he uttered this ſpeech, when he ſaw his dear wife and ſervants weeping before him; <hi>Why doe yee weep thus? cannot a man dye without all this adoe?</hi> and ſayth hee, I doe <hi>rely wholly upon the righteouſneſſe of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that time; he did renounce all his own works that ever he had done, deſiring to be accepted in Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:172634:26"/>
            <p>And thus I have done ſpeaking of him, and ſo ſpeaking longer to you; only I would entreat you to pray for his family: He hath been an inſtrument of good unto the countrey, and now he is gone, pray for his Family, pray good on his Family; that much good may ſtill come out of that Family.</p>
            <p>And what ſhall we ſay of our ſelves? what ſhall I ſay to you? I ſay againe, as I did before, Looſe not your opportunities: ſhall we ſuffer the time to condemn us, that was given to ſave us? we muſt either be ſaved in it, or condemned in it: ah then! let us time our buſineſſe aright for heaven: you that have no grace, get it: I ſay, get it; you that have any grace, uſe it for God, and increaſe it: uſe your grace to Gods glory: act more grace, and get more<note place="margin">Rom. 1. 17</note> grace. It is a ſad ſigne when men doe not go on in grace; the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of God (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) is revealed from faith to faith; That is, they which have faith, ſhall have more faith: therefore this is a fearfull ſigne that we have no faith nor grace, if God doth not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe our faith and grace in us.</p>
            <p>Againe, If men will ſleep and doe no good, God comes and takes away their gifts: <hi>Take his Talent from him</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>from the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſervant,</hi> in <hi>Act.</hi> 26. 18. You have God opening eyes, in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6. 10. you have God ſhutting eyes, in <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 1. you have God dreſſing trees, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 10. you have God hewing down trees, and in <hi>Mat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 28.</note> 21. there you have him curſing the tree, <hi>Never fruit grow on thee here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after:</hi> If thou neglect prayer God will take away the gift of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; if you will not exerciſe repentance, God will take away re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance it ſelfe from thee; thy graces ſhall drop away one after another, and ane vertue dye after another, untill the Soul dye too. Thus doth God ſmite the unprofitable ſervant, that crumbles away his time here, his opportunities here, and acts not for God: <hi>Take</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 29.</note> 
               <hi>away from him, even that which he hath;</hi> and then as the figtree began to wither, ſo doe his gifts begin to flag and paire in him; as if a worme were ſtill gnawing at them, his knowledge looſeth its relliſh, like a dying mans palate; his judgement in him ruſts like a ſword that is not uſed: His Faith withereth as if it were blaſted, &amp; the Image of death is upon all his profeſſion; he thinks (like <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>) to pray as he did, &amp; ſpeak as he did; he ſhakes himſelf to duty as at other times, but his ſtrength is gone from him. Wo to the Soul of ſuch a one; Soul-loſſes, and Soul-Judgements are the worſt.</p>
            <p>In one word, Sinners, wing your haſt, delay not, but home to God: your opportunities are flying, fly you as faſt home to God: let me argue the caſe with you as <hi>Abraham</hi> did with God, perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture (faith he) there be 50 righteous in <hi>Sodom,</hi> peradventue 20,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:172634:27"/> peradventure but 10, and wilt thou not ſpare it for theſe? as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> reckoned up the righteous that might have bin in <hi>Sodom,</hi> ſo give me leave to number your days; it may be thou haſt 20 years yet to live and wilt thou not ſerve God 20 years for a Crown of glory? 20 years ſervice is too little for ſo great a Crown of glory: when thou com'ſt to dye, thou would'ſt be ſaved for ever, and wilt thou not ſerve out 20 years to be ſaved an eternity? It may be thou haſt but 10 years yet to live, and wilt thou not ſerve God 10 years, who haſt ſerved a luſt twice 10? It may be thou haſt but 7 years yet to live, an apprentiſe ſerves out 7 years for a trade, and wilt thou not ſerve 7 years for an heaven? <hi>Jacob</hi> ſerved twice 7 for <hi>Rachel,</hi> and wilt thou not ſerve one 7 for Chriſt? It may be there are but five cards in all left in the deck, but 5 years yet to live, nay, it may be but 5 months, nay, it may be but five weeks, nay it may be but five days, nay, it may be but five hours, as ſoon as you are come home from burying the dead, you (it may be) may return your ſelves to be buried, ah then! is it not time for you to make haſt? you that have no grace, yet a little while, and you may looſe heaven, (and is it not time then for you to make haſt?) and you that have grace, yet a little while and you may arrive at heaven (and is it not time alſo for you to make haſt?) up then and be doing: you Saints, I ſay, up and be doing, it may be your worke is almoſt at an end; be not weary, pluck up your ſpirits; he which is tyred can crawl a little way; a little farther put on, a little farther yet, one ſtep more for a Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I would charge every one of you that have heard me this day, not to gather from any thing I have ſaid, that his oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie is paſt: for me up no ſuch concluſion: I doe not, I dare not ſay to the vileſt ſinner, that his opportunitie is paſt: Though thine opportunitie be paſſing away, yet I doe not ſay it is paſt away: this Sermon is not to ſhut any Sinner out of Heaven, but to haſten him towards heaven: becauſe you have loſt ſo many opportunities, I would haſten you to come in to Chriſt, whilſt there are any yet left: becauſe opportunties may be loſt, I would quicken you to come in, before all are gone: Sinner, yet take Chriſt, and God will yet receive thee; repent now, and God will ſave thee now. Say not, thy opportunity is gone, for God cals thee, linger and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay no longer; becauſe opportunity will be gone.</p>
            <closer>Deo ſoli Gloria.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
